<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fifth monarchy, or Kingdom of Christ, in opposition to the beasts, asserted, by the Solemn League and Covenant, several learned divines, the late General and Army, (viz.) in their declaration at Muslebrough, August 1650. wherein the old cause is stated, appeals made, the Scottish blood spilt, and the banners yet in Westminster-Hall witnessing the great decision then given on Christs side. Also, by a letter from the officers of the Army in England, to their brethren in Ireland, the 11 of May, 1653. justifying on Christs accompt, the dissolution of the Parliament; and consonant thereunto, the Generals speech to those that succeeded in the government, the fourth of July following ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E993_31</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207791</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866820</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866820</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85281)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E993[31])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fifth monarchy, or Kingdom of Christ, in opposition to the beasts, asserted, by the Solemn League and Covenant, several learned divines, the late General and Army, (viz.) in their declaration at Muslebrough, August 1650. wherein the old cause is stated, appeals made, the Scottish blood spilt, and the banners yet in Westminster-Hall witnessing the great decision then given on Christs side. Also, by a letter from the officers of the Army in England, to their brethren in Ireland, the 11 of May, 1653. justifying on Christs accompt, the dissolution of the Parliament; and consonant thereunto, the Generals speech to those that succeeded in the government, the fourth of July following ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 53, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Livewel Chapman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643). --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119106:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Fifth Monarchy, OR KINGDOM OF CHRIST, In oppoſition to the BEAST'S, Aſſerted, By the Solemn League and Covenant, ſeveral learned Divines, the late General and Army, <hi>(viz.)</hi> in their Declaration at <hi>Muſlebrough, August</hi> 1650. wherein the Old Cauſe is Stated, Appeals made, the <hi>Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> blood ſpilt, and the Banners yet in <hi>Westminſter-Hall</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the great deciſion then given <hi>on Christs ſide.</hi> Alſo, by a Letter from the Officers of the Army in <hi>England,</hi> to their Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the 11 of <hi>May,</hi> 1653. juſtifying on <hi>Chriſts accompt,</hi> the Diſſolution of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and conſonant thereunto, the <hi>Generals</hi> Speech to thoſe that ſucceeded in the Government, the fourth of <hi>July</hi> following. With a ſhort Application, and ſome brief Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals grounded on Scripture, in order to a laſting Settlement in this hour of diſtraction, the Foundations being out of courſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luk. 17.32.</bibl>
               <p>Remember Lots Wife.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Zach. 12.23.</bibl>
               <p>Behold, I will make Jeruſalem a cup of trembling unto all people; and in that day will I make Jeruſalem a burdenſome ſtone for all people: all that burden themſelves with it ſhall be cut in pieces, though all the people of the earth be gathered together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewel Chapman.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:119106:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119106:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT being manifeſt, that very many formerly engaged in the work of God, with their lives in their hands, in much appearing zeal and ſelf-denial, have (as their own expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is) warped aſide, ſoon forgetting his works, with their vows and promiſes in the day of diſtreſs, and falling in love with this worlds glory, the profitable pleaſant things thereof, have ſome of them in the laſt paſt years ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in oppoſition to ſuch as plead for the proſecution of the <hi>Lords</hi> work, and full following of him therein, ſometime loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them with reproaches of diſcontented, giddy, fanatick, Munſter-ſpirited people; It may not be unſeaſonable, when the leaſt ground of hope is given that they are not wholly fallen under the <hi>Lords</hi> diſpleaſure, ſo as no more to be owned in his work, in ſincere and unfeigned love to preſent to their view (if the <hi>Lord</hi> pleaſe to improve and bleſs it for their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther recovery) what was held forth formerly by the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> and ſome who in thoſe days were eſteemed <hi>Seers;</hi> conſented unto alſo in ſolemn Engagements by the diſperſed throughout the Land, lovers of God, his Ways and People, in aſſerting <hi>The Cauſe then contended for unto blood,</hi> and which ſtill remains as an Obligation unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be preſſing after.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="covenant">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119106:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Englands</hi> Engagement by all ſorts in the Solemn League and Covenant.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E Noble-men, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, Burgeſſes, Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Commons of all ſorts, of the Kingdom of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having before our eyes the Glory of God, and the Advancement of the Kingdom of</hi> JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Each of us for himſelf, with our hands lifted up-to the moſt high God, do ſwear that we ſhall ſincerely, really, and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, through the grace of God, in our ſeveral places and callings, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reformation of Religion in the Kingdoms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word of God, and the Example of the beſt Reformed Churches: and that we ſhall in like manner, without reſpect of perſons, endeavour the extirpation of Popery, Prelacy, (that is, Church-Government by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Chancellours and Commiſſaries, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Archdeacons, and all other Eccleſiaſtical Officers depending on that Hierarchy, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, Hereſy, Schiſm and Profaneneſs, and whatſoever ſhall be found contrary to ſound Doctrine and the Power of Godlineſs: leſt we partake in other mens ſins, and thereby be in danger to receive of their plagues; and that the Lord may be one, and his Name one, in the three Kingdoms,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this Covenant we make in the preſence of Almighty God, the Searcher of all hearts, with a true intention to perform the ſame, as we ſhall anſwer at the great day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed: moſt humbly beſeeching the Lord to ſtrengthen us by his holy Spirit for this end, and to bleſs our deſigns
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119106:3"/> and proceedings with ſuch ſucceſs, as may be deliverance and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his people, and encouragement to other Chriſtian Churches groaning under or in danger of the yoke of Antichriſtian Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to joyn in the ſame or like Aſſociation or Covenant, to the glory of God, the enlargement of the</hi> KINGDOM OF JESUS CHRIST, <hi>and the peace and tranquillity of Chriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Commonwealths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And conſonant hereunto, the Army in their Declaration of <hi>Muſlebrough,</hi> tell the Scots, <hi>We did many of us rejoyce at the Covenant, becauſe we found in it ſtrains towards theſe ends,</hi> viz. <hi>the deſtruction of Antichriſt, the advancement of the</hi> KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOM OF JESUS CHRIST, <hi>the Deliverance and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of his Church in the eſtabliſhment of his ordinances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us according to his Word, and the juſt civil Liberties of Engliſh men; although ſome being more enlightned, did apprehend it to be ſo mixt with worldly intereſt, that they juſtly ſeared the</hi> INTEREST OF JESUS CHIST <hi>would be but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretended to, and the interest of this world, and of Antichriſt himſelf, carryed on in a vizard, as we have ſince had abundance experience of. And let us in the preſence of the Lord further aſſure you, that we have already examined our Conſcience as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and have a clear aſſurance in our hearts, that he will countenance us in this action, and that we do not break any Covenant which we have ſworn before God, Angels and Men; but would be content (ſhould we not thereby idolize the Covenant) to march to any Engagement with you, if called thereunto by the Lord, with the Covenant on the tops of our Pikes: and let the Lord judge who hath obſerved the ends of the Covenant beſt, we or you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Mr. <hi>Burrough</hi>'s Sermon before the Houſe at the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Thankſgiving, <hi>Sept</hi> 7. 1641. for the peace concluded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> he hath this paſſage:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 44.</note> 
               <hi>God in this latter age is about to raiſe himſelf a glorious Name in the world, to ſet up his King upon his holy Hill, to make</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>the praiſe of the whole earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This that hath been already done,</hi> (viz. <hi>by the Scots and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Conjunction againſt King and Biſhops) is a preparation for, a fore-runner of, and a furtherance to, this great and glorious work of God: and bleſſed are thoſe men whom God ſhall pleaſe to make inſtrumental herein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The greatest-blow that ever was given to the Antichristian
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119106:4"/> Government, is that which now it hath had.</hi> Babylon is fallen, is fallen; <hi>ſo fallen, as it ſhall never riſe again in power. We hear a noyſe not onely from many waters, but from the thunder, ſaying,</hi> Hallelujah, the Lord God Omnipotent reigneth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.6. <hi>The voyce from the many waters, was from the people; but that was deſpiſed, contemned: but the voyce from the thunder, is from thoſe in places of dignity and power; and this voyce is terrible to the Adverſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin</hi> in his Sermons many years ſince at <hi>Antholins,</hi> upon <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.21,22. called, The world to come.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 28, 29.</note> 
               <hi>This Kingdom of Chriſt ſhall break in pieces and conſume all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdoms; this will eat out all the Monarchies and glory of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And not onely deſtroy Heatheniſm and Judaiſm, but will not ceaſe till he hath thrown down every rag, all that droſs and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that Antichriſt and Popery brought into the world: which diſpenſation we are now under; we are working up ſtill to a purer world, it is still this new world working up to its perfection, and Jeſus Chriſt will never rest till he hath not onely thrown out all the droſs of this world both of Doctrine and Worſhip, which conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the world ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h brought in; but for a further degree of this work, Jeſus Chriſt will not reſt till he hath brought in the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of men in the world to be ſubject to himſelf. The world (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture) conſists of Jews and Gentiles; and how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly doth the Apoſtle complain in his time of Gods outting off the Jews, the generality of the Nation being caſt off? and for the Gentiles, ſaith he,</hi> Who hath believed our report? <hi>There was a very few of them in compariſon, that did come in to Chriſt; but there will come a time when this new world ſhall have a further perfection, when the generality of man-kind, Jew and Gentile, ſhall come in to Chriſt. The world was made for him, and he ſhall have it before he has done.</hi> Rom. 11.26. All Iſrael ſhall be ſaved: <hi>there he tells us of a new world of the Jews; and for the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles he tells you, They ſhall be caſt in. The vail ſhall be taken from off all Nations,</hi> Eſay 25.1. There ſhall be one ſhepherd and one ſheepfold, of Jews and Gentiles; <hi>and that as large as all the world,</hi> John 10.16. <hi>This was never yet fulfilled. Read the Prophets, and you ſhall read ſtrange things of glorious times that ſhall be here on earth of all Nations coming into the Church, the mountain of the Lords houſe being ſet on the top of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119106:4"/> mountains, and all Nations flowing unto it; and of the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity that ſhall be: which was never yet fulfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, Mr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin</hi> in his Sermon before the Houſe, <hi>Feb.</hi> 25. 1645. call'd, The great Intereſt of States and Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 8, 9</note> Having been giving ſome inſtances how God had reproved Kings for the ſakes of his people, mentions that eminent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſubduing the four Kings, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. the Type of the four Monarchs, and the Saints ſubduing of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 10.</note> 
               <hi>Thus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>he began the world at firſt, and this very Victory is made a leading caſe, a ſtanding incouragement to the ſons of</hi> Abraham, <hi>the Saints, for ever after,</hi> Eſa. 41.2. Who raiſed up the righteous man from the Eaſt, (<hi>namely, this</hi> Abraham) and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to his foot, gave the Nations before him, and made him rule over Kings? (<hi>he means thoſe very Kings in the</hi> 14 <hi>of</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis:) he gave them as duſt to his ſword, and as driven ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his bow: he purſued them, and paſt ſafely. <hi>Did God do this for one or two of the Saints, and will he not go on? What ſaith the fourth verſe?</hi> Who hath wrought and done it, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Generations from the beginning? I the Lord am the firſt, and with the laſt I am he. <hi>I began to do thus with</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>and I will go on to do ſo even to the laſt for the ſons of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham: <hi>and that this is his meaning, read</hi> 8, 10, 14, verſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 32.</note> 
               <hi>As he caught the Jewiſh Princes and Prieſts in their crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt Chriſt; ſo will he for ever do thoſe that offer violence to his Saints, eſpecially when out of ſtate and worldly ends and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 39.</note> 
               <hi>And he ſhall overcome; for he is</hi> Lord of lords, and King of kings; <hi>and they that are with him are called,</hi> Choſen and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: <hi>you know the little Stone, Chriſt and his Saints, ſhall daſh all to pieces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 45.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt being peculiarly the King of Saints his intereſt is to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, defend and take part with them againſt all thoſe that do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign them, as he did the Nation of the Jews. It is his title, and his moſt royal title, and the greateſt title, that he is</hi> King of Saints: <hi>he preferreth it to his title of being</hi> King of Nations; <hi>that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth, and is not mentioned in compariſon of it. This therefore anſwerably muſt be his greateſt intereſt, which of all other he now purſueth. And therefore, if all thoſe Nations in which his Saints
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119106:5"/> are, do not bow to, and comply with it, he will ſhew himſelf that he is King of Saints and of Nations</hi> by ruining of them. <hi>As the greateſt intereſt of the Devils Kingdom is to perſecute thoſe that keep the Commandments of God, and the faith of</hi> Jeſus; <hi>ſo is it the greatest intereſt of the kingdom of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>to preſerve his Saints, and to confound thoſe that injure them: for he is King of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And further, in the old Teſtament, when this his Kingdom was further off, and longer to come, yet you ſee how ſtrongly he drove on this deſign then; but in the New Teſtament he is aſcended, and perſonally as man inveſted into it.</hi> We ſee Jeſus crowned with glory and honour, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. <hi>whoſe faith was as real in this, as our ſight can be; and he ſits there expecting, as thinking the time long till all his enemies are ſubdued,</hi> Heb. 10.13. <hi>which the ſame Apoſtle elſewhere interpreteth, and therein ſpeaks home to the point in hand, the putting down all Rule and Dominion that are oppoſite to his Saints,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.24,25. <hi>And accordingly in all thoſe Pſalms where ever his aſcention and investiture into his Kingdom at Gods right hand is propheſied of, there the ruine or converſion of Kings and Kingdoms are alſo ſpoken and propheſied of: read</hi> Pſalm 2. Pſalm 68. Pſalm 110. <hi>And let me add this to all, That as the ſhorter time</hi> Satan <hi>hath, the more is his rage; ſo the ſhorter time</hi> Chriſt <hi>hath, and the neerer he is to the poſſeſſion of his</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>the more is his zeal for his</hi> Saints, <hi>and indignation againſt his</hi> Enemies. <hi>His heart is ſet upon it, and the more eager doth his deſire become every day to attain his long-expected</hi> Kingdom, <hi>and to throw down all that oppoſe it; and therefore we ſee that in this latter age he hath made ſuch changes in the world; we have ſeen him do that in a few years, that he hath not done in a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years before: for he being</hi> King of Nations, <hi>he purſues his</hi> intereſt; <hi>and being more neer his</hi> Kingdom, <hi>he takes it with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence: we are now within the whirl of it, therefore his</hi> motions <hi>are rapt. Hence therefore all</hi> States <hi>and</hi> Kingdoms <hi>had need now (of all times elſe) to be inſtructed, and accordingly comply with this</hi> intereſt <hi>of Chriſt: it is more eſpecially now then ever, their greatest intereſt: it is well for us that Jeſus Chriſt is our</hi> King, <hi>who is the</hi> King of kings, and King of Saints; <hi>and withal, that he is ſo neer the enjoyment of his</hi> Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 44.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus Chriſt wins ground of us every day, and works us up age after age to a further Reformation, to more light and holineſs;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119106:5"/> and ſo he will do, till he hath perfectly overcome every Popiſh Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple out of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 57.</note> 
               <hi>I am confident of it, that Chriſt, that</hi> King of Saints, <hi>that is in heaven, he will not reſt till ſuch time as he hath made us one; if not injudgment, yet in forbearance; and that if we will not take warning, and will not agree it, that either Antichriſt or Jeſus Chriſt himſelf will come in upon us, and we ſhall be made to do it one way or other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 58.</note> I will make Jeruſalem a burdenſome ſtone for all people: all that burden themſelves with it ſhall be cut in pieces, though all the people of the earth be gathered together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. <hi>And you that are the Governours of</hi> Judah, <hi>ſhall be as a hearth of fire amongſt the wood, and a torch of fire in a ſheaf, all that oppoſe you, and riſe up againſt you, ſhall be but as ſo many ſtraws. Take a ſack of Straw great for Bulk, and lay it upon a few coales of fire upon a hearth; and what will become of them all? though they cover the fire a while, yet they will ſoon be conſumed and burnt up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 42, 43.</note> 
               <hi>The Saints have vouchſafed them by God a priviledge in ruling and governing this world, and the Providences of God therein: they are Privy-Counſellours to the great</hi> King of kings, <hi>who go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns all the States &amp; Kingdoms of this world: And God doth give the Saints a Commiſſion to ſet up and pull down by their prayers and interceſſions. The old Teſtament ſpeaks in a high language,</hi> Eſa. 45.11 Concerning the work of my hands command you me. <hi>Who ſpeaks this? the words before are,</hi> Thus ſaith the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly One of Iſrael, <hi>&amp;c. it would have been blaſphemy for us to have ſaid it.</hi> Then he goes on, bringing in the Lord ſpeaking thus; <hi>Behold, I that am thus your Maker, give you leave to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe by your prayers the great works of my hands which concern my children, my ſons; the affairs of Kingdoms, even ſo far as they relate to their good: and ſaith, upon this occaſion he raiſed up</hi> Cyrus, <hi>and pulled down the</hi> Babylonian Monarchy, <hi>becauſe they by their prayers had ſought this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> in his Sermon, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.27.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 14.</note> 
               <hi>All the preſent States of the world are cemented together by Antichriſtian lime; and unleſs they be ſo ſhaken as to have every cranny, ſearcht and bruſht, there will be no quiet habitations for</hi> Lord Chriſt <hi>and his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 25,</note> 
               <hi>The Heavens and the Earth of the Nations in their preſent constitution, are directly formed to the intereſt of Antichrist, which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119106:6"/> by notable advantages at their firſt moulding, and continued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuation, ever ſince, hath ſo riveted it ſelf into the very Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of them, that no digging or myning without an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake will caſt up the Foundation ſtones thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 35.</note> 
               <hi>Is it not evident to him that hath but half an eye, that the whole preſent conſtitution of the Governments of the Nations, is ſo cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Antichriſtian Morter from the very top to the bottom, that without a thorough ſhaking, they cannot be cleanſed?</hi> And a little after: <hi>This onely is certain, it (the ſaid ſhaking) ſhall not ſtop nor receive its period, before the intereſt of Antichriſtianity be wholly ſeparated from the power of theſe Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further ſaith, <hi>that no Atonement ſhall be made for the blood of the Saints ſlain under the notion of Hereticks, nor expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be allowed, whilſt a toe of the Image; or bone of the Beaſt, is left unbroken. And again, that which doth and ſhall ſtick upon Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates to their ruine, is not ſo much their own, or any other inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, as the very dregs of this Papal Antichristian intereſt thruſt into their Oaths and Obligations, for no other end in the world but to keep the Lord Jeſus out of his Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Book that gives an account of <hi>New Englands</hi> ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſome Laws for Government, publiſht for the uſe of that Colony, printed <hi>London</hi> —56.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though they humbly acknowledge, that the ſupreme power of making Laws, and of repealing of them, belongs to God onely; and that by him this power is given to Jeſus Chriſt as Mediator,</hi> Mat. 28.19. <hi>John</hi> 5.22. <hi>and that the Laws for holineſs and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are already made &amp; given us in the Scriptures, which in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters moral, or of moral equity, may not be altered by humane pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or authority;</hi> Moſes <hi>onely ſhewed Iſrael the Laws and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of God; and the Sanhedrim (the higheſt Court amongſt the Jews) muſt attend thoſe Laws: Yet Civil Courts and Rulers are the Miniſters of God, for the good of the people, and have power to declare, publiſh and eſtabliſh the Laws he hath made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Fox</hi>'s Martyrol. 1 Volume p. 139. is recorded an Epiſtle of <hi>Eleuthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſent to K. <hi>Lucius,</hi> the firſt Chriſtian K in <hi>England.</hi> 169.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You require of us the Roman Laws, and the Emperours to be ſent over to you, that you may practiſe the ſame, and put them in ure within your Realm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Roman Laws and Emperours we may reprove, but the Law of God we may not: ye have received of late through Gods mercy in the Realm of</hi> Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany, <hi>the Law and faith of Chriſt; you have with you within the Realm, both the parts of the Scriptures: out of them, by Gods grace, with the Counſel of your Realm, take ye a Law; and by that Law, through Gods ſufferance, rule your kingdom, according to the ſaying of the Pſalmiſt,</hi> O God, give thy judgments to the King and thy juſtice to the Kings ſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>he ſaid not The judgment and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119106:6"/>
            <head>The Letter of the General Council of the Army to their Brethren in their ſeveral Quarters and Gariſons, upon their march into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> 1650.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Chriſtian Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS it hath pleaſed our <hi>heavenly Father</hi> to <hi>call</hi> both you and us in theſe <hi>latter days</hi> to <hi>wait</hi> upon him in his <hi>great and terrible works,</hi> ſo the glory of his appearances hath been exceeding great in thoſe Services. And we truſt the <hi>record</hi> of his Love is kept with delight in your heart, as we deſire it may be upon our own for ever. And ſurely, the true <hi>uſe</hi> of thoſe precious Experiments where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath enriched us in this work, is to ſtrengthen our Faith, and quicken our hearts to a more cheerful attendance on <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>what further Service he ſhall appoint us.</hi> To what <hi>End</hi> cends that wonderful return of the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ers of his people in thoſe continued and ſwift Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes God hath afforded our Brethren in <hi>IRELAND,</hi> but to <hi>quicken</hi> us to a lively improvement of our intereſt in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by taking thoſe pledges of his Love as means to raiſe our hearts to <hi>expect</hi> much more? And what can be <hi>expected leſs from us</hi> after all ſuch full meals of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but to be ſtrengthened to <hi>Conflect with greater difficulties, and to follow the LAMB more fully then ever?</hi> We nave had a breathing time, while our Brethren have been bringing forth the deliverance of <hi>IRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND</hi> through ſore pangs: And now the Symptomes of <hi>travelling pain</hi> begin to take hold upon us; and as that glorion <hi>birth</hi> hath been thus far brought forth in <hi>IRELAND</hi> through the <hi>Prayers</hi> of the Saints, ſo we are encouraged to believe (while we finde the <hi>ſpirit of Prayer</hi> crying earneſtly for the accompliſhment of <hi>CHRISTS deſignes</hi> thorow all theſe dark diſpenſations) that the <hi>Cloſe</hi> will be the bringing forth of <hi>Zions deliverance:</hi> And to that end (deat Friends) we are hold in the <hi>Name of our Lord</hi> whom ye love, to provoke you to fervent Prayer (at this time) for the clear manifeſtation of the preſence of <hi>Chriſt</hi> with us, in whatever ſervice he ſhall call us unto. We are now again a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd <hi>by him</hi> to come forth into the field; but both our <hi>Work</hi> and the <hi>Iſſue</hi> is onely and wholly known to himſelf. <hi>Pray</hi> for us, that we may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant that <hi>Pillar of five before us,</hi> and the <hi>Cloud behind us;</hi> and that we may be found faithful Servants waiting onely upon our <hi>Lords good pleaſure,</hi> and ler both you and us be inſtant in <hi>Prayer,</hi> for the uniting of the hearts of all that fear the Lord in this and our Neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> that there may not be found any of the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119106:7"/> of the Juſt, joyning Iſſue with thoſe <hi>that ſupport the Beaſt, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the advancement of the KINGDOM of our LORD JESUS CHRIST, the King of Saints:</hi> But that ſome ſpecial and <hi>ſignal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery</hi> of the good Will of God to his people may now appear, in <hi>ſeparating the pretious from the vile, both in their</hi> counſels and actions: And it is moſt earneſtly deſired, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ervent Supplication and <hi>Prayer</hi> be made for all ſuch of us as ſhall be called to the management of <hi>Publick</hi> Affairs, that the <hi>Lord</hi> would make his way plain before us; That ſo in all our undertakings we may be ſubſervient <hi>to the affairs of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and walk in love (as becometh Saints) towards all diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied Brethren both in <hi>ENGLAND</hi> and <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> that our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared affection to them, as to the lot of Gods inheritance, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in all our demeanors towards them, and in theirs towards us; That ſo the <hi>enemies</hi> of <hi>CHRIST</hi> may be diſappointed, and theſe Clouds of Diviſion ſcattered, to the abundant Glory and Praiſe of God, and comfort of all his people. Who knows but yet (after the late too great Unchriſtian Differences between the Children of the ſame Father) this may be the day wherein ſhall be begun the <hi>fulfilling</hi> of thoſe glorious <hi>promiſes</hi> (which God hath made to his people) in the laſt days, <hi>And I will give them one heart and one way,</hi> Jer. 32.39. and, <hi>That Ephraim ſhall not envie Judah, and Judah ſhall not vex Ephraim,</hi> Iſa. 11.12,13,14 And that we may be active and conſtant in the <hi>work of the Lord,</hi> we farther provoke you to be earneſt with him on the behalf of all the Saints, and particularly for us, that our hearts may be taken off <hi>from the poor low things of this world: That we may not ſeek our ſelves, nor great things for our ſelves,</hi> but the <hi>glory</hi> and honour of JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST, who hath ſo gratiouſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owned us, and manifeſted his glorious preſence with us, through all the many temptations and tryals that we have been exerciſed under, and the ſore trouble our eyes have ſeen; All which he hath done, that he might <hi>humble</hi> us, and that he might prove us, to do us good in the latter end.</p>
            <p>And for all theſe ends, the Lord hath ſtirred up our hearts to ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the <hi>Fifth day</hi> of the next week, being the <hi>Thirtieth</hi> of this preſent Moneth, (<hi>May</hi> 30. 1650) as a ſolemn time to ſeek his Face, in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this work. Wherein (hoping you will joyn with us) we defire that both you and we may be humbled before the Lord, for all our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and latter evils that we have commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted, notwithſtanding the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his tender mercies towards us. It may be, ſince we have been at eaſe, we have contracted ruſt; the Lord make us every one ſenſible of the plague of his own heart, and grant that this may be a cleanſing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119106:7"/> day; that he would both reprove, and enable us to <hi>turn at his reproof;</hi> that ſo what employment ſoever the Lord calleth us unto, we may go to it leaving our ſins behind us: And let us with all fervency of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit pray that the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt would ſo <hi>pour out his Spirit</hi> upon us, that thereby our hearts being purged from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, our holy converſation may declare us to be the people of the Lord, yea, the <hi>Army of the LAMB, who is King of kings, and Lord of lords, whoſe followers are called, Choſen and ſaithful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince the Lord hath taught us, that to hang down the head as a <hi>Bulruſh</hi> for a day, is not ſuch a <hi>faſt</hi> as he hath choſen; we do fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therefore lay it upon our own hearts and yours, that if any (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officer or Souldier) be guilty of any <hi>proſaneneſs,</hi> to the <hi>ſcandal</hi> of the Goſpel; diſcovery thereof may be made, and ſuch courſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ken, as may be agreeable to the Goſpel, and Diſcipline of the Army.</p>
            <p>Further, that we uſe our utmoſt endeavours in our ſeveral places to reform thoſe groſs Enormities of Drunkenneſs, Swearing, open Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of the Lords day, and contempt of the Ordinances of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, which are too much to be ſound in the Army; that ſo as much as in us lyeth, we may purge out every <hi>accurſed thing</hi> from amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Dear Brethren, let us labour (through the power of the Spirit of Chriſt) to ſanctifie our ſelves and the <hi>Camp,</hi> for the <hi>LORD that is in the midſt of us,</hi> is a <hi>holy God;</hi> &amp; let us not too much <hi>preſume</hi> upon our former mercies, but well conſider what the Lord hath ſaid to his own people that were as neerly related to him as we can be, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.19 <hi>The Lord he is a holy and a jealous God, he will not forgive your tranſgreſſions and your ſins: if you forſake the Lord, and ſerve ſtrange Gods, then he will turn and conſume you, and do you hurt, after that he hath done you good:</hi> and again, <hi>Joſh</hi> 7.12 13. Read the words: as alſo <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 63.8,9,10. (Read the words:) Oh let theſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> and others to the ſame purpoſe, deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffect us; that ſo, whilſt we <hi>are uſed as a Rod of iron in Chriſts hand to daſh his enemies in pieces,</hi> we our ſelves may <hi>ſerve</hi> him with fear, and <hi>rej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yce</hi> with trembling. <hi>All that now ſeem to be on Chriſt's ſide, will not hold out unto the end.</hi> Be we faithful unto death, and Chriſt will give us a Crown of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> we ſhall earneſtly long to hear from you, to the end we may know how the Lord is pleaſed to affect your hearts with theſe things, and what impreſſions of his Spirit he ſhall (through his Word)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119106:8"/> ſet upon you after you have ſought his face with us about the ſame, that ſo we may further know (through you) his will concerning us. And we ſhall not fail in this and all other opportunities to ſeek the Lord for you, that you may be preſerved from every evil to his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Kingdom, that you may be kept blameleſs and harmleſs, the ſons of God without rebuke. And we beſeech you in the ſpirit of love and meekneſs, to ſtir up all that fear God, amongſt whom you converſe, (yea, though of different judgments, as to the form of Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to ſeek the Lord with us in theſe things: for ſure it cannot but be the deſire of every one that is a living member of Chriſts body, that the work of Chriſt ſhould proſper, and that all that fear the Lord may be of one heart and one mind, in the things that concern his great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, in a time when his <hi>work is to eſtabliſh his own Kingdom in the ruine of BABYLON,</hi> as (in the apprehenſion of many of his people) it is this day. Thus preſenting our moſt indeared affection to you, we heartily recommend you into the Boſome of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Chriſtian Friends and fellow Souldiers.</signed>
               <dateline>White-hall, <date>May 20. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>To all our dear Friends and fellow-Souldiers that fear the Lord.
<list>
                     <item>Will. Constable</item>
                     <item>William Roe</item>
                     <item>Rich. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>key</item>
                     <item>Griffith Lloyd</item>
                     <item>T. Harriſon</item>
                     <item>He. Haynes</item>
                     <item>Will. Style</item>
                     <item>Stephen White</item>
                     <item>Nath. Rich</item>
                     <item>W. Stane</item>
                     <item>Tobias Bridge</item>
                     <item>Nic. Lockier</item>
                     <item>Edw Whalley</item>
                     <item>Will. Goffe</item>
                     <item>Jo. Merreman</item>
                     <item>Thomas Hancock</item>
                     <item>Charles Fleetwood</item>
                     <item>Azariah Husbands</item>
                     <item>Will. Gough</item>
                     <item>George Joyce</item>
                     <item>Tho. Pride</item>
                     <item>John Blackwel</item>
                     <item>Edw. Orpin</item>
                     <item>Tho. Elſe</item>
                     <item>Math. Tomlinſon</item>
                     <item>Jo. Maſon</item>
                     <item>Robert Barrow</item>
                     <item>Tho. Bayley</item>
                     <item>John Okey</item>
                     <item>Jenkin Lloyd</item>
                     <item>Samſon Larke</item>
                     <item>Iſaac Knight</item>
                     <item>Paul Siſmey.</item>
                  </list>
               </salute>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>We deſire that what Return you make hereof, be directed to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Barkeſtead</hi> at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> to be by him communicated to the Officers at the Head-quarters.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119106:8"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION OF The Engliſh ARMY now in SCOTLAND.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>TO The people of <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> eſpecially thoſe a mong them, that know and fear the LORD;</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>We the Officers and Souldiers of the Engliſh Army, do ſend Greeting.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AT the <hi>beginning</hi> of the great and wonderful <hi>workings</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> in theſe two Nations of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> we the <hi>Under-Officers</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army now in <hi>Scotland,</hi> were (moſt of us, if not all) men of <hi>private Callings,</hi> and not at all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in matters of <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>State-affairs;</hi> but yet very <hi>many of us,</hi> in whom the Lord had begun to reveal himſelf in the Face of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> were ſenſible of the <hi>ANTICHRISTIAN Tyranny</hi> that was exerciſed by the late <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Prelates,</hi> over the <hi>Coxſciences,</hi> Bodies and Eſtates of the true <hi>Spiritual Church</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; namely, thoſe that were born again, and united to him hy his Spirit; who were then by that <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> crew, termed <hi>Puritans, Sectaries, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> &amp;c. and for <hi>not conforming</hi> to all the <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of their Nation-Church, were frequently impriſoned, baniſhed, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe grievouſly moleſted at the pleaſure of thoſe that then ruled amongſt us. Under theſe ſad ſufferings of the people of God, our ſouls mourned: and underſtanding by the manifold gracious promiſes in the Word of God, that a time of deliverance was to be expected to the <hi>Church of CHRIST,</hi> and deſtruction and ruine to <hi>BABYLON;</hi> Our hearts, together with all truly godly in <hi>England,</hi> were exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtirred up to <hi>pray</hi> to the <hi>Lord,</hi> even day and night, that he would <hi>Ariſe to dectroy ANTICHRIST,</hi> and to ſave his people. Whilſt this <hi>Spirit</hi> of Prayer was poured forth upon Gods people in <hi>England,</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts are made upon <hi>Scotland,</hi> to bring them to a <hi>conformity</hi> in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Worſhip, by endeavouring to <hi>impoſe</hi> upon them a <hi>Popiſh Service-Book,</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119106:9"/> which was through the great goodneſs of God, by his people in <hi>Scotland,</hi> rejected; which made the wrath of the late King and his Prelates, wax ſo hot againſt them, ſo as <hi>Scotland</hi> had no other way to preſerve it ſelf, but by coming into <hi>England</hi> with an Army; which the godly in <hi>England</hi> did not then count an Invaſion to deſtroy <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> no more then they do this our preſent march for the ruine of <hi>Scotland:</hi> but rejoyced to ſee ſome appearing againſt that ANTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHRISTIAN power that had <hi>perſecuted</hi> the Saints; and were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, That the LORD <hi>was come forth to anſwer</hi> the many <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> that were then <hi>poured,</hi> and pouring forth for that purpoſe: and therefore ſo far as we had any opportunity, farthered the deſigns of that Army; ſome of us hazzarding our lives, by ſpreading their Book, intituled, <hi>The SCOTS INTENTIONS, and pleading for the justneſs of their Proceedings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us remember, how the Lord was pleaſed gratiouſly to <hi>anſwer</hi> the <hi>prayers</hi> of his people at that time, in their deliverance from the <hi>Army</hi> raiſed by the late <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Prelates,</hi> for the deſtruction of all the people of God in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi> inſomuch, That ſoon after, <hi>Scotland</hi> ſits in Peace, enjoying their former Liberties, without being impoſed upon by the <hi>Antichriſtian Prelacy</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and <hi>England</hi> obtains a <hi>Parliament;</hi> to whom they have opportunity to complain of their grievances, and through the great goodneſs of God ſo conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that grievances are heard, and overtures made to the late King for their redreſs: which was ſo irkſome to his Oppreſſing, Tyrannical and Bloody Spirit, that he again betook himſelf to overthrew the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> by force; and to that end, entertains the Officers of the Army that had gone forth againſt our Brethren of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and withdrawing himſelf from his Parliament, an appearance of a Civil War begins; which being made known to us the inſeriout Officers and Souldiers of this Army, (then in our <hi>private</hi> Callings) we found our <hi>hearts extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſtirred up by the LORD</hi> to aſſiſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt the <hi>King;</hi> being abundantly <hi>ſatisfied in our judgments and conſciences, that we were called forth by the Lord, to be inſtrumental to bring about that, which was our continual prayer to God,</hi> (viz.) <hi>The DESTRUCTION of ANTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHRIST, and the deliverance of his CHURCH and PEOPLE.</hi> And upon this ſimple accompt, we <hi>engaged,</hi> not knowing the deep policies of worldly <hi>Stateſmen,</hi> and have ever ſince hazarded our lives in the <hi>high</hi> places of the field, (where we have ſeen the <hi>wonders of the Lord</hi>) againſt all the oppoſers of this work of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> whom we have all along ſeen going with us, and making our way plain before us. And
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119106:9"/> having <hi>theſe</hi> things ſingly in our eye, namely, the <hi>deſtrustion of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> the <hi>advancement of</hi> the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Reiormation of <hi>his Church,</hi> in the Eſtabliſhment of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances amongſt them in purity according to his Word; and the <hi>juſt civil Liberties of Engliſhmen:</hi> we did many of us rejoyce at the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> becauſe we found in it a ſtrain towards theſe ends, although ſome being more enlightned, did apprehend it to be ſo <hi>mixt</hi> with worldly intereſt, that they juſtly <hi>feared,</hi> the <hi>intereſt of JESUS CHRIST</hi> would be onely <hi>pretended</hi> to, and the <hi>interests of this world,</hi> yea, of <hi>ANTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHRIST</hi> himſelf <hi>carried</hi> under a vizard, as we have ſince had abundant experience of; which hath made us (we confeſs) not to <hi>idoliz;</hi> the <hi>Covenant,</hi> (as we fear too many do) though we truſt, it will appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, Angels and Men, that we ſhall ever <hi>purſue</hi> its <hi>true</hi> and <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ends,</hi> according to the plain candid meaning thereof; though we do not upon every occaſion <hi>urge the Covenant,</hi> (as we ſee every party, though as far different as light and darkneſs, apt to do) the Lord ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by his Word and by his Spirit convinced us of our <hi>duty</hi> therein, though there had been no ſuch <hi>Covenant</hi> at all entred into.</p>
               <p>But when we ſaw that under <hi>pretence of the Covenant,</hi> a corrupt party in Parliament, by their worldly policy, after the War was ended in <hi>England,</hi> and the late Kings party ſubdued, with the loſs of <hi>thouſands</hi> of the lives of <hi>Saints, (whoſe death is precious in the ſight of the Lord)</hi> did endeavour to ſet up the <hi>King</hi> upon his <hi>own</hi> terms, and with him to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh a <hi>National Church Government, not</hi> in all things <hi>agreeable to the</hi> WORD OF GOD, but is deſtructive to the juſt <hi>Liberties</hi> of the true Spiritual <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> which he hath by his own moſt <hi>precious blood</hi> purchaſed for them, and is now come forth to beſtow upon them: which did ſufficiently demonſtrate it ſelf by the dealings of the then <hi>Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builders</hi> with the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, in and about <hi>London,</hi> that were then threatned to be diſſolved, and Laws made to prevent the Communion of Saints with one another, except only in that one pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Form then about to be eſtabliſhed, to the aſtoniſhment of many of us that had lifted up our hands to God, and ſworn to endeavour a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation according to the Word of God; and therefore after much waiting upon God by prayer, and examining our own hearts, about the ends and ſincerity thereof, we were abundantly ſatisfied, that it was not onely lawful, but our duty to keep our Arms in our hands, till the ends beforementioned ſhould be accompliſhed; and to that purpoſe, the Army, whereof we are a part, did refuſe to disband, did march up to <hi>London</hi> to propoſe to the Parliament a way of Eſtabliſhment that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119106:10"/> might be more for the carrying on of the ends of Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though therein we were not at that time ſucceſsful, yet moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully and graciouſly preſerved by the Lord, and extraordinarily convinced, after much ſeeking the Face of God, that our failing was in endeavouring to ſet up the King upon any terms, he being a man of ſo much blood, that the Lord would have no peace with him, nor any that ſhould go about to eſtabliſh him: Whereupon, after his own hard heart had hindred him from yeilding to any overtures that were made to him by the Parliament, through whom all the Armies Propoſals were to be tendered and a ſecond War more dangerous then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer contrived by him, and his Son now with you, together with thoſe in <hi>Scotland</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ated us of the Army of <hi>England</hi> under the name of Sectaries, being by the unſpeakable goodneſs and mighty power of God waded through, and a ſecond teſtimony given from Heaven, to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the proceedings of his poor ſervants againſt that bloody Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian brood, though with the loſs of many precious Saints; we were then powerfully convinced, that the Lords purpoſe was to deal with the late King as a man of blood: And being perſwaded in our conſciences, That he and his Monarchy was one of the ten horns of the Beaſt ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12,13,14,15. and being witneſſes to ſo much of the innocent blood of the Saints that he had ſhed in ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Beaſt; and conſidering the loud cries of the ſouls of the Saints under the Altar, we were extraordinarily carryed forth to deſire Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon the King, that man of blood: And to that purpoſe petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned our Superiour Officers, and the Parliament, to bring him to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: which accordingly, by an high hand of Providence was brought to paſs; which Act we are confident the Lord will own, in preſerving the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> againſt all Kingdoms and Nations, that ſhall adventure to meddle with them upon that account. When God executes his judgements upon Malefactors, let none go about to reſiſt: When he brings forth thoſe his Enemies that will not ſuffer Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to be King in the midſt of his Saints, and breaks them in pieces like a Potters veſſel; let not <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor any other Nation ſay, What doſt thou? We fear they have been too buſie already: the Lord that ſees the ſecrets of all hearts, knows, the compliance of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with the late Kings Iſſue now with you, was in order to diſturb the Peace of <hi>England,</hi> for being Gods Executioners upon a bloody Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and a ſupporter of the Throne of the Beaſt: But bleſſed be the Lord, the crafty are taken in their own ſuare: <hi>England</hi> ſits in peace, whilſt <hi>Scotland</hi> receives into their chief City, their new King, at the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119106:10"/> very hour wherein an Army had marched 300 miles, is ſacing them at the very gates. We wiſh our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> eſpecially thoſe that truly fear the Lord, would conſider theſe things, and not ſlight the Providences of God ſo much as they do: When <hi>Scotland</hi> choſe new gods, and would have a King out of a Family that God had rejected, then was War in the Gates: And though we do not think Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces alone, a ſufficient rule for Gods people to walk by, yet we do know that the Lord ſpeaks to his people by his Providence as well as by his Word; and he is angry with his people that do not take notice thereof, and promiſeth bleſſing to thoſe that do, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 107. and the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end.</p>
               <p>And here give us leave (not in a boaſting ſpirit, but in meekneſs and fear) to tell you, That we are perſwaded we are poor unworthy inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Gods hand to break his Enemies, and preſerve his people. You have acknowledged us in your own papers to be a rod of iron to daſh in pieces the Malignants: but withal ſay, We muſt now be broken in pieces, becauſe we now ſet our ſelvs againſt the Lor of Gods inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Let us here ſpeak for our ſelves; yea, the Lord ſpeak for us, who knows our hearts, and all our ways: we value the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, who are the Lot of Gods inheritance, ten thouſand times above our own lives; yea, we do bleſs the Lord, we are not onely a Rod of Iron, to daſh the common enemies in pieces, but alſo a hedge (though very unworthy) about Chriſts Vineyard; and if we know our own hearts, where ever the Lot of Gods inheritance ſhall appear to be found in <hi>Scotland,</hi> we ſhall think it our duty to the utmoſt hazard of our lives, to preſerve the ſame: But if there be any that have taken counſel together againſt the Lord, and againſt his Anoynted, whom the Lord hath decreed to ſet upon his holy Hill of <hi>Zion;</hi> we are perſwaded the Lord hath brought us hither as inſtruments, through which he will ſpeak to them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure. VVe deſire it may be known to you our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that we are not Souldiers of Fortune, we are not meerly the ſervants of men, we have not onely proclaimed Jeſus Chriſt, the <hi>King</hi> of Saints, to be our <hi>King</hi> by Profeſſion; but deſire to ſubmit to him upon his own terms, and to admit him to the exerciſe of his Royal Authority in our hearts, and to follow him whitherſoever he goeth, he having of his own good will entred into a Covenant of Grace with his poor Saints; and be aſſured, it is he that leadeth us into <hi>Scotland,</hi> as he hath done in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> And therefore we do in the ſpirit of brotherly love, and of the fear of the Lord, beſeech you to look about you; for our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119106:11"/> Lord Jeſus is coming amongſt you as a refiners fire, and as Fullers ſope: and bleſſed are thoſe in whom the leaſt dram of ſincerity ſhall be found.</p>
               <p>VVe have a Paper directed to us from the people of <hi>Scotland,</hi> it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been publickly made known to us at the head of our Regiments; wherein we are firſt deſired to conſider the lawfulneſs of our marching into <hi>Scotland.</hi> We bleſs God, we did that before we came; and are abundantly ſatisfied, that we are brought hither by the Lord: nay, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of us lying under temptations of fleſh and blood, and going about to frame excuſes to take us from this march, found, that to have ſtaid behind, had been to have turned our backs upon Jeſus Chriſt, and to have deprived our ſelves of much ſweet communion with God, that now through his goodneſs we do enjoy.</p>
               <p>VVe have alſo conſidered the Arguments, by which you go about to weaken the grounds of the Parliaments, and our Superiour Officers, leading us into <hi>Scotland;</hi> and muſt needs give you this Return: That we are ſtill abundantly eſtabliſhed in this belief, that what the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England</hi> hath done in ſending us into <hi>Scotland,</hi> hath been of abſolute neceſſity to preſerve themſelves from being deſtroyed in their Religion and Liberties, which they have been at ſo much coſt both of Blood and Treaſure, to purchaſe and preſerve: and therefore by the way we muſt needs tell you, that we cannot endure to hear them call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>A pretended Parliament;</hi> which we deſire you to take notice of, that if you write to us again, you would ſpeak more reverently of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of our Nation, or elſe we ſhall eaſily think you will upon every occaſion be ready to invade <hi>England,</hi> that you may ſet up an Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which you may call lawful.</p>
               <p>And let us, as in the prefence of the Lord, further aſſure you, That we have already examined our conſciences, as before the Lord, &amp; have a clear aſſurance in our hearts, That he will countenance us in this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that we do not break any Covenant which we have ſworn before God, Angels and Men; but could be contented, ſhould we not thereby idolize the <hi>Covenant,</hi> to march to any Engagement with you, if called thereunto by the Lord, with the <hi>Covenant</hi> on the tops of our Pikes; and let the Lord judge who hath obſerved the Ends of the Covenant beſt, you or we? Yet we do acknowledge, we have not been the exact Performers, though not the wilful breakers thereof: our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences alſo bear us record, we do above any thing in the world, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Union of the two Nations; and it is our prayer dayly. That thoſe that fear the Lord in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> may become one in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119106:11"/> the hand of the Lord, and joyn together in the advancement of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and throwing down, and trampling upon the Seat of the Beaſt. VVhy ſhould not <hi>Scotland</hi> as well as <hi>England,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce to ſee the horns of the Beaſt cut off, that we may joyn together, to hate the VVhore, and to <hi>burn her fleſh with fire?</hi> The Lord is our witneſs, (whom we fear) we come not to oppreſs you, or ſhed your blood; we have cryed to the Lord, again and again, to prevent it: we have ſent you our Declaration of Love to the People of God in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which ſome amongſt you, though they pretended to anſwer, yet do moſt injuriouſly and unchriſtianly keep from their ſight; nay, moſt falſly miſ-repreſenting us as a people come with intentions to deſtroy the poor inhabitants, and that we are left of our God to be deſtroyed: but we have made our prayer to the Lord, and made known before him their ſayings, who have told the people of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that God hath forſaken us; and therefore bid them perſecute and take us, for now the Sectaries day is come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the Lord is ſtill with us, he is our Refuge, and a preſent help in trouble, ready to be found: we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, the cry of the oppreſſed in <hi>Scotland</hi> will be heard, and wo to thoſe that are the Cauſe thereof. Our Quarrel is ſtill againſt Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, the Root whereof is now, through the evil policy of ſome Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, become the head of <hi>Scotland.</hi> VVe dare not quarrel with thoſe whoſe hearts are upright with Jeſus Chriſt, and faithful and loving to <hi>England;</hi> but with thoſe who are moſt treacherous and falſe to both: and therefore we daie not any of us, though tempted thereto by your papers, be ſo carnally wiſe, as to deſert the Cauſe and VVork of Jeſus Chriſt, in which we have hitherto been ſo long and ſo miraculouſly carried on. Do you think we are men ſo weakly principled, as to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded without the leaſt ſtrength of Argument to deſert the intereſt of out own Nation, and expoſe thouſands of the precious Saints of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to be trampled upon as the dirt in the ſtreets, when the Lord is about to put on their beautiful garments, and to make them a praiſe in the earth? Or can we (think you) betray our ſuperiour Officers, in whom we ſee ſo much of the ſweet Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt, into your hands, whoſe mouths are opened wide to devour them? VVe pray you not to wait for ſuch a thing. The Lord hath brought us hither by his Providence, and upon him we ſhall with confidence depend, till we ſee a glorious Iſſue, which we humbly and heartily deſire may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the effuſion of any more blood; and (if it be the Will of God) both ſpeedy and comfortable to you and us, that we may return with joy into <hi>England,</hi> and leave <hi>Scotland</hi> rejoycing that an Engliſh Army hath
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119106:12"/> been amongſt them: which poſſibly may be the ſooner effected, were you and we ſuffered to confer, and open our hearts one to another: we do believe much of the bitterneſs of ſpirit would be allayed in our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> did they know how exceedingly we are ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the pens and tongues of many of your <hi>Kirk-men,</hi> concerning our Religion and faith towards God, which though we may not vainly boaſt of, yet according to the Apoſtles direction, we are ready to give an anſwer to the meaneſt Chriſtian in <hi>Scotland that ſhall ask a reaſon of the faith and hope that is in us, with meekneſs and fear.</hi> And indeed, we account our beſt way of contending with thoſe ſlanders, is to pray the Lord to make our hearts ſound in his Statutes, that we be not aſhamed, that ſo we <hi>ſanctifying the Lord God in our hearts, and having a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, they that ſpeak evil of us as of evildoers, may be aſhamed whilſt they falſly accuſe our good converſation in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus have we in the naked plainneſs of our ſouls, opened our hearts unto you, our dear Brethren, that fear the Lord in <hi>Scotland,</hi> where ever you be found, whether in the higheſt Councils, or the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Cottages, who though you now be ſcattered, the Lord will in his due time bring you together, and bind you up as his Jewels, and make you one with thoſe that fear the Lord amongſt us: which the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and in him our God and Father alſo, bring to paſs in his due time; and in the mean time make both you and us wiſe to underſtand the things that concern the exalting of Chriſts <hi>Kingdom:</hi> That in all our undertakings we may be ſubſervient to the Affairs of Jeſus Chriſt; and above all things, take heed how we ſtir up any of the powers or ſtrength of this world to deſtroy one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Prince of Peace, be with you.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From the Leaguer at <hi>Muſlebrough,</hi> 
                     <date>Auguſt 1. 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>VVhich ſaid Declaration, was ſent to the Scots, incloſed in a Letter of the General to this purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That the under-Officers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in the Engliſh Army had deſired him to ſend to them this their Declaration; which he tells them was not a crafty politick one, but a plain ſimple ſpiritual one, ſuch as it is, God knoweth; and God alſo will in due time make manifeſt. And do we multiply theſe words as men? Or do we them for the Lord Chriſt and his peoples ſake? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> concluding, Your humble Servant, <hi>O. Cromwel.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119106:12"/>
               <p>And further, in their Declaration, <hi>Aguſt</hi> 16. in anſwer to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the general Aſſembly, they conclude thus: We ſhall cloſe with our hearty ſupplications, That the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt would in due time caſt down all the Earthly Combinations of all ſorts of men that ſet up themſelves and their own corrupt intereſt in the room of that Scepter of Righteouſneſs which he hath given in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of his Son. Publiſhed by the ſpecial appointment of the Council of State.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>For the Right Honourable, <hi>Charles Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> Eſq; Commander in chief of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be communicated to our dear friends the Officers under his Command.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Honourable, and our dear Chriſtian Friends!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WHen we conſider the many and wonderful things, which the Lord hath of late years brought to paſs in theſe three Nations, in the ſubduing of great Armies, and caſting down all the ſtrong Holds of the Enemy, in pouring <hi>contempt upon Princes,</hi> and <hi>great men, that have not kiſſed,</hi> but oppoſed the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> in the work he hath been and is ſtill carrying on in the World; and in taking <hi>down and altering forms of Government,</hi> that have been in theſe Nations, <hi>both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> we cannot but cry out, <hi>Great and marvellous are thy works, Lord God Almighty: juſt and true are thy ways, thou King of Saints; who ſhall not fear thee, O Lord, and glorifie thy Name? for thy judgments are made manifeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As you were witneſſes of, and active in ſome of thoſe great changes that have formerly been made, ſo we doubt not but you have (though at a diſtance) felt the late <hi>Earth-quake,</hi> and have heard of the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Diſſolution of the Parliament: which yet being ſo great a Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, we thought it our duty to ſend you this Letter, to the end we might therein let you know the frame of our hearts, and how deſirous we are, that you and we, may, in the midſt of the great diſpenſations of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119106:13"/> God, ſtill continue ſtedfaſt in one ſpirit; that ſo, if it be the Will of t he Lord, we may be further inſtrumental in bringing about thoſe things which may be to the glory of God, the good of his people, and the peace and welfare of the Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>It would require more time then we have now to ſpare, to give you a particular and full account, of all the grounds and reaſons upon which this great Action was undertaken; and therefore therein we ſhall refer you to the Declaration of the Lord General and his <hi>Council of Officers, of the</hi> 22 <hi>of</hi> April <hi>laſt,</hi> and to your own obſervations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ill management of Affairs by the late Parliament: onely we ſhall ſay, that this laſt dangerous remedy of a Diſſolution, was not uſed, till all other ways had been by us aſſayed, and by them rejected. And therefore, after four years expectation (ſince the change of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment) finding no performance of thoſe things that tend to the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of the Commonwealth, in Peace and Righteouſneſs: and being abundantly ſatisfied upon long experience, <hi>That the Parliament, as it was conſtituted, were ſo far from being the inſtruments of perfecting the work</hi> of the Lord, that <hi>this whole Cauſe was in great danger to periſh under their hands,</hi> for which <hi>there hath been ſo vaſt an expence of Blood and Treaſure.</hi> After much ſeeking the <hi>Face of God,</hi> &amp; taking counſel one with another, it was generally apprehended, that the only way left us, was, To endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor a ſpeedy Change in the <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> that ſo the perpetual fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Parliament may be prevented; and the Government laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſhoulders of ſuch men as might hopefully give us the fruit of all our Labour and Blood, and encourage good men to be ſtill willing to hazard their lives againſt the common Enemy; which, as things lately ſtood, many had little heart to do. And it was in our hearts, to ſeek this thing in ſuch a way, that the Parliament might have had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of it; but it pleaſed not the Lord to give them an heart to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to the Motions made in order thereunto, by the General, in the name of himſelf and his Officers, many of which were preſent; but rather to endeavour a haſty and inconſiderate paſſing of an Act for a new Repreſentative; the danger whereof, was very evident, and was by the General, at a Meeting with many of the Members of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Officers of the Army, abundantly demonſtrated to them, which yet the next day was ſo earneſtly and precipitantly perſiſted in, that it was found neceſſary to put them to a ſudden Diſſolution, which alſo we hope the <hi>Lord</hi> will make the Medium to future good: of <hi>which there is the more expectation, becauſe it hath pleaſed God, who hath the hearts of all men in his own hand, ſo to order the ſpirits of men, that not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119106:13"/> onely the Army and Fleet, do moſt unanimouſly concur and agree, but alſo the generality of all ſorts of people do rejoyce therein; inſomuch that there is not the appearance of the leaſt diſturbance.</hi> And it is the continual and fervent prayers of all the people of God, that this great Change, may have the extraordinary bleſſing of God upon it.</p>
               <p>By this incloſed Declaration, you will perceive what proviſion is made for the preſent management of Affairs, till perſons of approved Fidelity and Honeſty may be called to take upon them the <hi>Supreme Authority</hi> of this Commonwealth: which being done, we may have cauſe to hope, the Lord will make them a future bleſſing to us.</p>
               <p>Dear Friends, we are perſwaded this is the Lords own work, and ought to be mavellous in our eyes: the Lord hath once and again pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led down the Mighty from their ſeats, and <hi>we truſt it is that himſelf may raign:</hi> and therefore, let the earth rejoyce, and theſe our Iſlands be glad thereof; for though clouds and darkneſs be round about him, yet Righteouſneſs and Judgment are the habitation of his Throne. The Lord is terrible in his doings, therefore the guilty world will tremble, but <hi>Sionſhall hear and be glad, and the daughters of Judah ſhall rejoyce becauſe of his judgments. Let us therefore</hi> (dear Brethren) <hi>ſerve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling; for we are not without hope,</hi> that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is the <hi>King of Saints,</hi> will henceforth ſhew himſelf to be the <hi>King of Nations</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p>We do not doubt but the Lord will make your hearts as ours, in this great buſineſs, and that as the Lord hath wonderfully ſtirred up the heart of his Excellency the Lord General, to put himſelf upon <hi>God,</hi> in this great undertaking, for the intereſt of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>people;</hi> ſo we ſhall adhere to him and one to another therein. We know your ſincere love to Chriſt and his people is ſuch, that we ſhall uſe no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments unto you, but onely mind you, <hi>That when the Lord called you to the ſervice of</hi> Ireland, <hi>at a ſolemn meeting of the Officers deſigned for</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>with thoſe that remained here, after that we had, with many prayers and tears recommended one another into the boſome of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>we did alſo in the preſence of each other, and before the Lord, ſolemnly ſubmit our ſelves and all our affairs to be whollyat his diſpoſe; reſolving through the influence of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in all our politick undertakings, not to ſeek our ſelves but the advancement of the affairs and kingdom of our Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. In this Spirit, and with theſe Reſolutions, we parted with one another, and the Lord hath bleſſed us hitherto, and lo! we are yet alive, though thouſands of our dear Brethren who engaged with us, are dead. <hi>The Lord grant we may with our lives be inſtrumental to carry on and preſerve that Cauſe and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119106:14"/> which was by them valued above their lives; and whoſe blood cryeth loud to us to perſevere therein unto the end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us therefore, we beſeech you, provoke both you and our ſelves, not to conſult with carnal reaſon in theſe great Mutations, but let us labour by faith to ſee the Lord carry on his own work, and to manifeſt our ſelves, whom God hath called and choſen to theſe ſtations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſtand, to be alſo faithful in doing the work unto which he ſhall appoint us.</p>
               <p>Dear Brethren, the work hath hitherto been to break and pull down, which every one almoſt ſeemeth to be good at; but it's now the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of good men, that Building and Eſtabliſhing work ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; for which yet, there are not in our view many fit, and therefore it will be your duty and ours, to pray without ceaſing, that thoſe whom God ſhall call to the Government, may be men full of the Holy Ghoſt, and of Power, and may have his continual preſence in the carrying on of ſo great a work, on the iſſue whereof depends (as we are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) the intereſt of the Saints, throughout the whole world.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Lord</hi> keep our hearts cloſe to himſelf, that ſo, however things go about, we may be found walking as becometh the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in faith towards God, in love one towards another, and in Peace and Righteouſneſs towards all men. Which that we may do, let us earneſtly beg your continual and ſervent Prayers, even as we deſire to make mention of you, as often as we encompaſs the Throne of Grace, in the Name of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in whom we are,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your moſt affectionate Friends and Brethren,
<list>
                        <item>John Lambert</item>
                        <item>John Disbrow</item>
                        <item>Edward Whalley</item>
                        <item>Thomas Harriſon</item>
                        <item>William Conſtable</item>
                        <item>Adrian Scroop</item>
                        <item>Nathaniel Rich</item>
                        <item>Matthew Tomlinſon</item>
                        <item>Philip Twiſleton</item>
                        <item>Thomas Pride</item>
                        <item>Thomas Cooper</item>
                        <item>William Goffe</item>
                        <item>Ralph Coblet</item>
                        <item>Francis Hacker</item>
                        <item>Charles Worſley</item>
                        <item>Francis White</item>
                        <item>Thomas Kelſey</item>
                        <item>Thomas Biſcoe</item>
                        <item>Robert Swallow</item>
                        <item>Roger Alſopp</item>
                        <item>Arthur Husbands</item>
                        <item>Griffith Lloyd</item>
                        <item>John Maſon</item>
                        <item>Thomas Saunders</item>
                        <item>John Hodgſon</item>
                        <item>Jeoffrey Elatſon</item>
                        <item>Edward Orpin</item>
                        <item>Samuel Lark</item>
                        <item>John Caitnes</item>
                        <item>John Wigan</item>
                        <item>Edward Walley</item>
                        <item>Richard Mereſt</item>
                        <item>John Robinſon</item>
                        <item>Edmund Chillenden</item>
                        <item>George Smithſon</item>
                        <item>William Packer</item>
                        <item>William Style</item>
                        <item>Francis Allen</item>
                        <item>William Farley</item>
                        <item>William Malin</item>
                        <item>Richard Hatter.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119106:14"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Phil. 1.18.</bibl>
                     <p>What then? notwithſtanding every way, whether in pretence or in truth, Chriſt is preached, and I therein do rejoyce, yea, and will rejoyce.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The ſpiritually wiſe cannot but ſoon diſcern, whether the breathings of the Lords holy Spirit are more viſible in this, then the Armies late (as it's called) repentance; and the chief Officers may do well to conſider, whether it were not better with them, when they avouched the Lord to be their God, even Chriſt to be the King of Nations, then ſince (changing their glory into ſhame) they are found amongſt the ſcoffers, ſaying, <hi>Where is the promiſe of his coming?</hi> and they may obſerve the diſſolution of the Parliament: however many now would have it accompted onely a precipitate Act of their General, yet it had a very ſerious and deliberate owning by them, who can no otherwiſe be juſtified in that or formet undertakings, thereby following the Lord in paths untroden, contradictory to this old Antichriſtian worlds frame and conſtitution, or as their own expreſſion in their Letter is, <hi>By reſigning themſelves and all their affairs to be wholly at the Lords diſpoſe, reſolving through the influence of his Spirit in all their publick undertakings, not to ſeek themſelves, but the advansement of the Affairs and Kingdom of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> But how faithfully this hath been obſerved, the light in their own conſciences can beſt ſatisfie them, if they dare ask the queſtion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119106:15"/>
            <head>The Lord General CROMWEL His SPEECH, At the Council-Chamber, to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then Aſſembled by Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <hi>July</hi> 4. 1653.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Suppoſe the <hi>Summons</hi> that hath been inſtrumental to bring you hither, gives you well to underſtand the cauſe of your being here. Howbeit, having ſomething to impart, which is <hi>an Inſtrument</hi> drawn up by the conſent and advice of the principal Officers of the Army, which is a little (as we conceive) more ſignificant, then that other of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; we have that here to tender you. And we have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what likewiſe further to ſay to you, for our own <hi>exoneration;</hi> and we hope it may be ſomewhat further to your ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And therefore ſeeing you ſit here ſomewhat uneaſie, by reaſon of the ſcantneſs of the Room, and the heat of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I ſhall contract my ſelf with reſpect to that.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Series of Providence in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> I have not thought it amiſs, a little to mind you of that <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Providence,</hi> wherein the Lord hitherto hath diſpenſed wonderful things to theſe Nations, from the beginning of our Troubles to this very day. If I ſhould look much back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, we might remember the ſtate of affairs as they were before the ſhort, and that which was the laſt Parliament: in what a poſture the things of this Nation ſtood, doth ſo well, I preſume, occur to all your memories and knowledges, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119106:15"/> I ſhall not need to look ſo far backward, nor yet to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of thoſe Hoſtile actions that paſt between the King that was, and the then-Parliament. And indeed, ſhould I begin this labour, the things that would fall neceſſarily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, would rather be fit for a Hiſtory, then for a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, at this preſent.</p>
            <p>But thus far we may look back: <note place="margin" type="runSum">Winnowing the Army.</note> You very well know, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter divers turnings of affairs, it pleaſed God, much about the midſt of this War, to <hi>winnow,</hi> as I may ſo ſay, the Forces of this Nation, and to put them into the hands of <hi>men of other Principles then thoſe that did engage at the firſt.</hi> By what ſtrange providences that alſo was brought about, would ask more time then is allotted me, to remember you of. Indeed, there are Stories that do recite thoſe tranſactions, and give Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of matter of fact: but thoſe things wherein the life and power of them lay, thoſe ſtrange windings and turnings of Providence, thoſe very great appearances of God, in croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and thwarting the deſignes of men, that he might raiſe up a poor and contemptible company of men, neither <hi>vers'd in Military affairs, nor having much natural propenſity to them,</hi> 
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The life and power of the work, lay in the Armies owning a principle of godlieneſs.</note> 
               <hi>even through the OWNING OF A PRINCIPLE OF GODLINESS, of Religion: which ſo ſoon as it came to be own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the ſtate of affairs put upon that foot of account, how God blest them, and all undertakings, by the riſing of that moſt improbable, deſpicable, contemptible means,</hi> for that we muſt for ever own, you very well know.</p>
            <p>What the ſeveral ſucceſſes have been, is not fit to mention at this time, neither; though I muſt confeſs I thought to have enlarged my ſelf upon this Subject, <note place="margin" type="runSum">Conſidering Providence a ſpecial duty, and a means to ſtrengthen faith for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> 
               <hi>foraſmuch as the CONSIDERING the WORKS of GOD, and the OPERA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF HIS HANDS, is a principal part of our duty, and a great encouragement to the ſtrengthning of our hands, and of our faith for that which is behinde.</hi> And then having given us thoſe marvellous diſpenſations, amongſt other ends, for that was a moſt principal end, as to us, in this revolution of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and <hi>iſſues</hi> of thoſe Succeſſes God was pleaſed to give this Nation, and the Authority that then ſtood, were very <hi>great things</hi> brought about; beſides thoſe dints that were upon thoſe Nations and places where they were carryed on, even in the <hi>Civil affairs,</hi> to the bringing <hi>offenders to juſtice,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119106:16"/> the GREATEST; to the bringing the ſtate of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to the Name at leaſt of a Commonwealth; to the ſearching and <hi>ſifting</hi> of all <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Perſons;</hi> 
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Proceeds with King, Peers and Commons.</note> the <hi>KING</hi> removed, and brought to juſtice, and many great ones with him; the Houſe of <hi>PEERS</hi> laid aſide; the Houſe of <hi>COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS,</hi> the Repreſentative of the people of <hi>England,</hi> it ſelf, winnowed, ſifted, and brought to a handful, as you may very well remember.</p>
            <p>And truly, God would not reſt there, (for, by the way, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be fit for us to entitle our failings and miſcarriages to our ſelves, yet the gloriouſneſs of the work may well be attributed to God himſelf, and may be called <hi>His strange work.</hi>)</p>
            <p>You may remember well, that at the change of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment there was not an end of our Troubles, although that year were ſuch things tranſacted, <note place="margin" type="runSum">Memorable 1648.</note> as indeed made it to be the <hi>moſt MEMORABLE YEAR</hi> (I mean, 1648.) that ever this Nation ſaw; ſo many Inſurrections, Invaſions, ſecret Deſignes, open and publick Attempts, quaſh'd in ſo ſhort a time, and this by the very ſignal appearances of God himſelf, I hope we ſhall never forget.</p>
            <p>You know alſo, (as I ſaid before) that as the effect of that <hi>Memorable year,</hi> 1648. was to lay the Foundation of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Delinquents</hi> to puniſhment; ſo it was of the <hi>change</hi> of the <hi>Government:</hi> although it be true, if we had time to ſpeak, the <hi>carriages of ſome in truſt,</hi> in <hi>moſt eminent truſt, was ſuch,</hi> as would have fruſtrated to us the hopes of all our undertakings, had not <hi>God</hi> miraculouſly <hi>prevented:</hi> 
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Cloſure with King, God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</note> I mean, by that <hi>Cloſure</hi> that would have been endeavoured with the <hi>King,</hi> whereby we ſhould have put into his hands all that Cauſe and Intereſt we had oppoſed, and had had nothing to have <hi>ſecured</hi> us, but a <hi>little piece of Paper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Nations ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> 1651.</note> But things going on, how it pleaſed the Lord to keep this Nation in exerciſe both at Sea and Land, and what GOD wrought in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> you likewiſe know, until the Lord had finiſht all that trouble, upon the matter, by the marvellous <hi>ſalvation wrought at</hi> WORCESTER.</p>
            <p>I confeſs to you, I am very much troubled in my ſpirit, that the neceſſity of affairs doth require that I ſhould be ſo ſhort in theſe things, becauſe I told you before, This is <hi>the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119106:16"/> leaneſt</hi> part of the <hi>Tranſaction,</hi> to wit, an Hiſtorical Narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; there being in every Diſpenſation, (whether the <hi>Kings going from the Parliament,</hi> the <hi>pulling down the Biſhops, purging the Houſe at that time by their going away to aſſiſt the King, change of Government</hi>) whatever it was, not any of thoſe things, but hath a remarkable point of Providence ſet upon it, that <hi>he that runs may read.</hi> Therefore I am heartily ſorry, that in point of time I cannot be particular in thoſe things, which I did principally deſigue this day, thereby to provoke and ſtir up your hearts and mine to gratitude and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Paſſages ſince <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter.</hi>
               </note> I ſhall now begin a little to remember you the <hi>PASSA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GES that have been tranſacted ſince WORCESTER</hi> ſight; whence coming with my Fellow-Officers and Souldiers, we expected, and had ſome reaſonable confidence, that our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations ſhould not be fruſtrate; <hi>That the Authority that then was, having ſuch a Hiſtory to look back unto,</hi> ſuch a God that <hi>appeared for them ſo eminently, ſo viſibly,</hi> that even our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies many times confeſs'd that God himſelf was engaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, or they ſhould never have been brought ſo low, nor diſappointed in every undertaking: [for that may be ſaid (by the way) <hi>had we miſcarried but once, where had we been?</hi>] <note place="margin" type="runSum">Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſuch mercies, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the true intereſt on the three Nations.</note> I ſay, We did think, and had ſome reaſonable confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that coming up then, the <hi>mercies</hi> that God had ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the <hi>expectations</hi> that were in the hearts of all good men, would have prompted thoſe that were in Authority to have done <hi>thoſe good things,</hi> which might by honeſt men have been judged a <hi>return</hi> fit for ſuch a God, and <hi>worthy of ſuch mercies;</hi> and indeed, a diſcharge of duty to thoſe, for whom all theſe mercies have been ſhewed, that is, the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the three Nations, <hi>the true intereſt of the three Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if I ſhould now labour to be particular in <hi>enumerating ſome buſineſſes that have been tranſacted from that time, till the diſſolution of the late Parliament,</hi> indeed I ſhould be upon a Theme would be very troubleſome to my ſelf. <note place="margin" type="runSum">The neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and duty on the Army for diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> For I muſt ſay for my ſelf and Fellow-Officers, we have rather deſired and ſtudied <hi>healing,</hi> then to <hi>rake into ſores,</hi> and look backward, to render things in thoſe colours that would not be very well pleaſing to any good eye to look upon. Onely this we muſt ſay, for our own <hi>exoneration,</hi> and as thereby laying ſome foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119106:17"/> for the making <hi>evident</hi> the <hi>neceſſity</hi> and <hi>duty that was incumbent upon us, to make this laſt great Change,</hi> I think it will not be amiſs to offer a word or two in that, not taking plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to rake into the buſineſs, were not there ſome kind of neceſſity ſo to do.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Which they ſought to heal and prevent,</note> Indeed we may ſay, without commending our ſelves, I mean my ſelf and thoſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> that have been engaged in the Military affairs, that upon our return, we came fully bent in our hearts and thoughts, to deſire and uſe all <hi>fair and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful means we could,</hi> to have <hi>had the Nation to reap the fruit of all</hi> that blood <hi>and treaſure that had been expended in this cauſe;</hi> and we have had many deſires and thirſtings in our ſpirits, to finde out ways and means, wherein we might any ways be inſtrumental, to help it forward; <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. By Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi> 1652.</note> and we were very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for a long time, ſo much as to Petition, till <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, or thereabouts, we never offered to Petition. But ſome of our then Members, and others, having good acquaintance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to divers members of the Parliament; we did from time to time ſollicite, that which we thought (if there had been no body to prompt them, no body to call upon them) would have been liſtned to, out of ingenuity and integrity in them that had opportunity to have anſwered our expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: And truly, when we ſaw nothing would be done, we did (as we thought, according to our duty, remind them by a <hi>Petition;</hi> which Petition, I ſuppoſe the moſt of you have ſeen, which we delivered either <hi>in</hi> July <hi>or</hi> Auguſt <hi>laſt: what effect that had, is likewiſe</hi> very well known; the truth is, we <hi>had no return at all;</hi> all the ſatisfaction for us, was, but a few words given us; <hi>the buſineſſes petitioned for, moſt of them</hi> (we were told) <hi>were under conſideration; and thoſe that were not, had very little or no conſideration at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finding the people diſſatisfied, in every corner of the Nation, and bringing home to our doors the non-performance of thoſe things that had been promiſed,</hi> and were of due to be performed; we did think our ſelves concerned; we endeavoured as became ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men, to keep up the reputation of honeſt men in the world; <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. By a mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with ſome of the Parliament; 10 or 12 times beſeeching them to diſcharge their duty and truſt to God and Man freely: But all in vain.</note> and therefore we had divers times endeavoured to obtain a meeting with divers Members of Parliament; and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119106:17"/> truly we did not begin this, till <hi>October</hi> laſt; and in thoſe <hi>meetings</hi> did in all faithfulneſs and ſincerity, <hi>beſeech them,</hi> that they would be <hi>mindful of their duty to God and man,</hi> and of the <hi>diſcharge of their truſt</hi> to God and man: I believe theſe Gentlemen that are many of them here, can tell, that we had at the leaſt <hi>ten or twelve meetings;</hi> moſt humbly <hi>begging and beſeeching</hi> them, that of their own accords, they would do thoſe good things, that had been promiſed; that ſo it might appear, they did not do them by any ſuggeſtion from the Army, but of their own ingenuity: ſo tender were we to preſerve them in the reputation and opinion of the people, to the uttermoſt. And having had many of thoſe meetings, and declaring plainly, that the iſſue would be the judgment and diſpleaſure of God againſt them, the diſſatisfaction of the People, and the putting things into a confuſion: Yet how little we did prevaile, we well know, and we believe is not unknown to you.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. By cloſe conſidering what other way to have. recourſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> At the laſt, when we ſaw indeed that things would not be laid to heart, we had a ſerious conſideration amongſt our ſelves, what <hi>other way to have recourſe unto;</hi> and when indeed we came to thoſe <hi>cloſe conſiderations,</hi> they began to take the <hi>Act of the NEW REPRESENTATIVE</hi> to heart, and ſeemed exceeding willing to put it on; the which, had it been done, or would it have been done, with that integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with that caution, that would have ſaved this Cauſe, and the Intereſt we have been ſo long engaged in; there could nothing have happened to our judgments, more welcome then that would have been: <note place="margin" type="runSum">Neceſſity of their diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. 1. From their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to perpetuate themſelves.</note> But finding plainly, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment of it, was not to give the people that Right of choyce, although it had been, but a ſeeming right, either the ſeeming to give the people that choyce intended and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, to recrute the Houſe, the better to PERPETUATE THEMSELVES: And truly, having divers of us been ſpoken to, to that end, that we ſhould give way to it; a thing to which we had a perpetual averſation; which we did abominate the thoughts of; we always declared our judgements againſt it, and our diſſatisfaction; but <hi>yet they would not hear of a New REPRESENTATIVE, before it lay three years before them,</hi> without proceeding with one line conſiderably in it: They that could not endure to hear of it; then, when we came to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119106:18"/> our <hi>cloſe conſiderations,</hi> then inſtead of <hi>protracting,</hi> they did make as much <hi>prepoſterous haſt,</hi> of the other hand, and ran into that extremity; and finding that this ſpirit was not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God, and that the whole weight of this cauſe (which muſt needs have been very dear unto us, who have ſo often adventured our lives for it; and we believe is ſo to you) when we ſaw plainly that there was not ſo much conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how to aſſert it, or to provide ſecurity for it; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to croſs theſe, that they reckoned the moſt troubleſome people they had to deal with, which was the Army, which by this time was ſufficiently their diſpleaſure: when we ſaw this, that had power in our hands, <hi>truly to let the buſineſs go to ſuch an iſſue as this, was to throw back the cauſe into the hands of them we firſt fought with;</hi> we came to this firſt concluſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves, that if we had been fought out of it, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity would have taught us patience; <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. That the Army might not be found Traytors to God &amp; Man</note> but to <hi>be taken from us ſo unworthily, we ſhould be rendered the worſt people in the world, and we ſhould become</hi> TRAYTORS BOTH TO GOD AND MAN. And when God had laid this to our hearts, and that we found the intereſt of his <hi>people was grown cheap,</hi> and not laid to heart, and if we came to competition of things, the cauſe even among themſelves, would (even almoſt in every thing) go to the ground: this did add more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to us, that there was a duty incumbent upon us. And truly, I ſpeak it in the preſence of ſome that are here, that were at the cloſe conſultations (I may ſay) as before the Lord, the thinking of an act of violence was to us worſe than any Engagement that ever we were in yet; and worſe to us than the utmoſt hazard of our lives, that could be; ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing were we, ſo tender were we, ſo deſirous were we if it were poſſible, that theſe men might have quit their places with honour: And truly, this I am the longer upon, becauſe it hath been in our hearts and conſciences, our Juſtification, and hath never yet been imparted thorow to the Nation; and we had rather begin with you to do it, then to have done it before; and do think indeed, that theſe tranſactions be more proper for a <hi>verbal communication, then to have put it into writing:</hi> I doubt, whoſoever had put it in writing, would have been tempted to have dipt his pen in anger and wrath. But affairs being at this poſture, that <hi>we ſaw plainly and evidently</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119106:18"/> in ſome Critical things, <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. The cauſe of the people deſpiſed by them.</note> that <hi>the Cauſe of the people of God was a deſpiſed thing;</hi> truly then we did believe, that the hands of <hi>other men,</hi> muſt be the hands that <hi>muſt be truſted</hi> with it; and then we thought high time for us, to look about us, and to be ſenſible of our duty. If I ſhould take up your time, to tell you, what inſtances we have to ſatisfie our Judgments and Conſciences, that theſe were <hi>not vain imaginations,</hi> and things that were petitioned for; but that fell within the compaſs of our certain knowledge and ſence; ſhould I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat theſe things to you, I ſhould do that which I would avoid, to take into theſe things too much: <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. A corrupt ſelf-ſeeking Spirit in them.</note> onely this, if any body were in competition, for any place of real and ſignal Truſt, how hard and difficult a thing it were to get any thing to be carried, without making parties; without things indeed, <hi>unworthy of a Parliament.</hi> And when things muſt be carried ſo in a Supreme Authority; indeed, <hi>I think, it is not as it ought to be.</hi> But when it came to other Trials, in that <hi>Caſe of Wales,</hi> which I muſt confeſs, for my own part, I ſet my ſelf upon, if I ſhould inform what diſcountenance that buſineſs of the poor <hi>people of God,</hi> there had; <note place="margin" type="runSum">5. Diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God in <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </note> who had watching over them, men like ſo many <hi>wolves,</hi> ready to catch the <hi>Lamb,</hi> aſſoon as it was brought out into the world: <hi>how ſignally they threw that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs under foot, to the diſcountenancing of the honeſt people there,</hi> and to the <hi>countenancing of the malignant party of this Commonwealth.</hi> I need but ſay, it was ſo; many have felt by ſad experience it was ſo, who will better impart that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to you, which (for my ſelf and fellow-Officers) I think it was as <hi>perfect a trial of their</hi> ſpirits, as <hi>any thing;</hi> it being known to many of us, that <hi>God kindles a ſeed there: indeed hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be parallell'd ſince the Primitive times.</hi> I would this had been all the inſtances; <note place="margin" type="runSum">Good to Gods people under the ſeveral forms never intended.</note> but finding which way their ſpirits went, and finding that <hi>good was never intended to the people of God,</hi> (I mean when I ſay ſo) that large comprehenſion of them, <hi>under the ſeveral forms of godlineſs in this Nation;</hi> when I ſaw that <hi>tenderneſs</hi> was forgotten, to them all (though it was very true, that by <hi>their hands</hi> and means, through the bleſſing of God, they ſate were they did) and affairs, (not to ſpeak it boaſtingly) had been inſtrumentally brought to that iſſue they were brought to, by the hands of thoſe poor creatures; we thought this an evil requital. I will not ſay they were
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119106:19"/> at the uttermoſt pitch of Reformation, although I could ſay, that one thing, the REGULATION of the LAW ſo much <hi>groaned under</hi> in that poſture it now is in; there was many words ſpoken for it, we know many moneths together, was not time enough, to paſs over one word called Incumbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: I ſay, finding that this was the ſpirit and complexion of them, that though theſe were faults, for which no man ſhould have dared to lift his hand, ſimply for their faults, and fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <note place="margin" type="runSum">Neglect of reforming the Laws.</note> when yet we ſaw their intendment was to <hi>perpetuate themſelves, and men of this ſpirit,</hi> for ſome had it from their own mouths, from their own deſignes, who could not endure to hear of being diſſolved; this was an high breach of Truſt, <hi>if they had been a Parliament never violated,</hi> fitting as free, and as clear as ever any ſat in <hi>ENGLAND;</hi> yet if they would go about to <hi>perpetuate themſelves,</hi> we did think this to be ſo <hi>high a breach of truſt,</hi> as greater could not be. And we did not go <hi>by gueſs</hi> in this; and to be out of doubt in it, we did (having that conference among our ſelves, whereof we gave ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt) we did deſire once more, the night before the difſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, [and it had been in our deſires, ſome two or three days before] that we might ſpeak with ſome of the principal perſons of the houſe, that we might with ingenuity open our hearts to them, to the end we might be either convinced of the ground of their principles and intentions, to the good of the Nation; or if we could not be convinced, they would hear our offer, or expedient to prevent this miſchief; and indeed we could not prevail for two or three days, till the night before the diſſolution: there is a touch of this in that our DECLARATION; we had often deſired it, at that time we attained; there were above Twenty of them who were members not of the leaſt conſideration, for intereſt and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, with whom we deſired to diſcourſe thoſe things, and had diſcourſe with them; and it pleaſed the Gentlemen Officers of the Army to deſire me to offer their ſence to them; and indeed it was ſhortly carryed thus; we told them, that the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of our deſire to wait upon them, was, that we might know from them, what ſecurity lay in the way of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſo haſtily with their Repreſentative, wherein they had made a few qualifications, (ſuch as they were) and how the whole buſineſs ſhould be executed, we have no accompt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119106:19"/> of; and we deſired them they would be pleaſed, and we thought we had an intereſt in our lives, eſtates, and families, as well as the worſt people of the Nation; and that we might be bold, to ask ſatisfaction in that; and if they did proceed in honeſt ways, as might be ſafe to the Nation, we might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce therein: When we preſt them to give ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this, the <hi>Anſwer</hi> was made, that <hi>nothing could be good to the Nation, but the continuance of this Parliament.</hi> We wondred that we ſhould have ſuch a return: we ſaid little to that.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing they would not give us that which might ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us that their way was honeſt and ſafe, they would give us leave to make our Objections; We did tell them, that we thought that way they were going in, would be impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable: we could not tell them how it would be brought to paſs, to ſend out an Act of Parliament into the Country, to have qualifications in an Act to be the Rules of Electors and Elected, and not to know who ſhould execute this; deſired to know whether the next Parliament were not like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of all <hi>Presbyters?</hi> 
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">No qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to ſeclude Presbyters &amp; Newters</note> Whether thoſe Qualifications would hinder them? or <hi>Newters?</hi> and though it be our deſire to value and eſteem of that Judgment, onely they having been as we know, having <hi>deſerted this cauſe and intereſt, upon the Kings account,</hi> and upon that cloſure between them and the Neighbour-Nation; we do think, we muſt confeſs, we had as good have delivered up our Cauſe into the hands of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as into the hands of intereſſed and byaſſed men; for it is one thing to live friendly and brotherly; to bear with, and love a perſon of another judgment in Religion: another thing to have any ſo far ſet into the ſaddle upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, as that it ſhould be in them, to have all the reſt of their Brethren at mercy. Having had this diſcourſe, making theſe Objections, of bringing in <hi>Neuters,</hi> or ſuch as ſhould impoſe upon their Brethren, or ſuch as had given teſtimony to the Kings party: and objecting to the danger of it, in drawing the concourſe of all people, to arraign every individual perſon, which indeed did fall obviouſly in, and the iſſue would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have been, the putting it into the hands of men that had little affection to this Cauſe. The <hi>Anſwer</hi> again was made, [and it was confeſſed by ſome, that theſe Objections
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119106:20"/> did lye; But anſwer was mde] by a very eminent perſon, at the ſame time, as before, <hi>that nothing would ſave the Nation, but the continuance of this Parliament.</hi> This being ſo, we humbly propoſed an expedient of ours, which was indeed, to deſire that the <hi>Government</hi> being in that condition it was, &amp; things being under ſo much ill ſenſe abroad, and ſo likely to come to conſuſion in every reſpect, if it went on; ſo <hi>we deſired they would devolve the truſt over to perſons of honour and integrity, that were well known, men well-affected to Religion, and the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest of the Nation:</hi> which (we told them, and was confeſſed) had been no new thing, when theſe Nations had been under the like hurly-burly and diſtractions; and it was confeſſed by them, it had been no new thing; we had been at labour to get <hi>preſidents</hi> to convince them of it. And we told them theſe things we offered out of that <hi>deep ſenſe</hi> we had of the good of the Nations, and the <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt;</hi> And being Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to that, <hi>nothing would ſave the Nation but the continuance of that Parliament</hi> (although they would not ſay, they would perpetuate it) at that time leaſt of all.</p>
            <p>But finding their endeavours did directly tend to it, they gave us this <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That the things we had offered, were of a tender and very weighty conſideration. They did make <hi>Objections</hi> how we ſhould raiſe money, and ſome other Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: we told them, that that we offered as an expedient, becauſe we thought better then that for which no reaſon was, or thought would be given; we deſired them, to lay the thing ſeriouſly to heart: they told us, they would take conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of theſe things till the morning, that they would ſleep upon them. And I think that there was ſcarce any day, that there ſat above 50 or 52 or 53. At the parting, two or three of the chief ones, the very chiefeſt of them, did tell us, <hi>that they would endeavour the ſuſpending the proceedings of the Repreſentative, the next day, till they had a further conference;</hi> and we did acquieſce; and had hope, if our expedient would take up a loving debate, the next day we ſhould have ſome ſuch iſſue of our debate, as would have given a ſatisfaction to all.</p>
            <p>They went away late at night: and the next morning we conſidering how to order that which we had to offer to them; when they were to meet in the Evening, word was brought,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119106:20"/> they were proceeding with a <hi>Repreſentative,</hi> with all the <hi>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſs</hi> they could: we did not believe perſons of ſuch qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity could do it: a ſecond and a third Meſſenger told us, they had almoſt finiſhed it, and had brought it to that iſſue with that haſt, that had never been before; leaving out the things that did neceſſarily relate to <hi>due qualifications,</hi> as we have heard ſince, reſolved to make it <hi>a paper Bill,</hi> not to <hi>ingroſs</hi> it; that they might make the quicker diſpatch of it. Thus to have thrown all the liberties of the Nation into the hands <hi>that</hi> never bled for it; upon this account, we <hi>thought</hi> it our duty not to ſuffer it: and upon this the Houſe was diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Old Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Cauſe.</note> This we tell you, <hi>that</hi> you may ſo know, <hi>that</hi> what hath been done in the diſſolution of this <hi>Parliamont,</hi> was as neceſſary to be done, as the preſervation of this cauſe; <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. The Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> and that neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity that led us to do that, hath brought us to this iſſue, of exerciſing an extraordinary way, and courſe, to draw your ſelves together upon this accompt, that you are men who know the Lord, and have made obſervations of his marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous diſpenſations, and may be truſted with this cauſe. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, for I ſhall not acquaint you further with that that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to your taking upon you this great buſineſs, that being contained in this Paper, in my hand, which I do offer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to you, to read, having done that which we thought to have done upon this ground of neceſſity, which we know was not feigned neceſſity, but real and true, <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. That the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might not fall.</note> to the end the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment might not be at a loſs, <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. To mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyal of the Army.</note> to the end we might mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to the world the ſingleneſs of our hearts, and integrity, who did thoſe things not to graſp after the power our ſelves, to keep it in a Military hand, no not for a day, as far as God enables us with ſtrength and ability, to put it into the hands that might be called from ſeveral parts of the Nation; this <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> I ſay, and we hope may ſay, for our ſelves, <hi>this integrity of laboring to deveſt the Sword of the power and authority in the civil adminiſtration of it, hath been that that hath moved us, to conclude of this courſe;</hi> and having done that, we think we cannot with the diſcharge of our conſciences, but offer ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what unto you, as I ſaid before, for our own exoneration, it having been the practiſe of others who have voluntarily and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119106:21"/> out of ſenſe of duty deveſted themſelves, and devolved the Government into the hands of others, it having been the practice, where ſuch things have been done, and very conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to reaſon, together with the authority, to lay a charge, in ſuch away, as we hope we do, and to preſs to the duty, which we have a word or two to offer to you. Truly <hi>GOD hath called you</hi> to this work, by (I think) as wonderful provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences as ever paſt upon the ſons of men in ſo ſhort a time. And truly, I think, taking the Arguments of neceſſity, (for the Government muſt not fall) take the appearances of the Will of God in this thing, I am ſure you would have been loath it ſhould have been reſigned into the hands of <hi>wicked men and enemies.</hi> I am ſure, God would not have it ſo: It comes therefore to you <hi>by way of neceſſity,</hi> it comes to you by the way of the <hi>wiſe Providence of God,</hi> though through weak hands; and therefore, I think, it coming through our hands, though ſuch as we are, it may not be taken ill, if we offer to you ſomething as to the diſcharge of that truſt which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon you: And although I ſeem to ſpeak that which may have the face of a <hi>charge,</hi> it is a very humble one; and he that means to be a <hi>ſervant to you,</hi> who are called to the exerciſe of <hi>the ſupreme Authority,</hi> to diſcharge that, which he conceives is his <hi>duty,</hi> in his own and his fellows names; to you I hope who will take it in good part. And truly, I ſhall not hold you long in that, becauſe I hope it is written in your hearts, to approve your ſelves to God onely; This <hi>Scripture</hi> I ſhall remember to you, which hath been much upon my ſpirit, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 11 and 12 <hi>verſe, Yet Judah ruleth with God, and is faithful among the Saints;</hi> 
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Charges the old Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their faſting and praying to compaſs God about with lyes.</note> it is ſaid before, <hi>Ephraim did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs God about with lies, and Iſrael with deceit:</hi> how God hath been compaſſed about with Faſtings and Thankſgivings, and other exerciſes and tranſactions, I think we have all to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: why truly you are called by God, <hi>to rule with him,</hi> and for him; and you are called to be <hi>faithful with the Saints,</hi> who have been ſomewhat inſtrumental to <hi>your call: he that ruleth over men,</hi> (the Scripture ſaith) he <hi>muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly, it is better to pray for you, then to counſel you in that, that you may exerciſe the judgment of mercy, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119106:21"/> truth; I ſay, it is better for you to do it, then to adviſe you, to ask wiſdom from heaven for you; which I am confident many thouſands of Saints do this day, and have done, and will do, through the permiſſion of God, and his aſſiſtance, to adviſe you; onely truly I thought of a Scripture likewiſe that ſeems to be but a Scripture of common application to every man as a Chriſtian, wherein he is counſelled to <hi>ask wiſdom;</hi> and he is told <hi>what</hi> is <hi>that wiſdom</hi> that <hi>is from above,</hi> it <hi>is pure, peaceable, gentle, caſie to be intreated, full of good fruits, without partiality, without hypocriſie;</hi> and my thoughts ran thus upon this, that the executing of the <hi>judgment</hi> of truth, [for that is the judgment that you muſt have Wiſdom from above for, and that is pure, that will teach you to execute the <hi>judgment</hi> of <hi>truth,</hi> and then] if God give you hearts to be <hi>eaſie to be intreated,</hi> to be <hi>peaceable ſpirits,</hi> to be <hi>full of good fruits,</hi> bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good fruits to the <hi>Nation,</hi> to men as men, to the people of God, to all in their ſeveral ſtations; this wiſdom will <hi>teach</hi> you to execute the judgment of Mercy and Truth. And I have little more to ſay to this; I ſhall rather bend my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for you in that behalf (as I ſaid before) and I know many others do alſo. Truly, the <hi>judgment of truth</hi> will teach you, to be as juſt towards an Unbeleever, as towards a Beleever; and it is our duty to do ſo. I confeſs, I have often ſaid it foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly, If I would miſcarry, I would rather do it to a Beleever then to an Unbeleever; perhaps it is a Paradox; but let us take heed of doing it to either, exerciſing injuſtice to either: if God fill our hearts with ſuch a ſpirit as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> had, which was not onely a ſpirit for the <hi>Beleevers</hi> among the people of God, but for the <hi>whole</hi> people, he would have <hi>dyed</hi> for them; and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> to his Countrymen according to the fleſh, he could have <hi>dyed</hi> for them: truly this will help us to execute the judgment of Truth and Mercy alſo.</p>
            <p>A ſecond thing is, to deſire you would be <hi>faithful with the Saints;</hi> and I hope, whatever others may think, ought to be to us all matter of tejoycing, that as one perſon our Saviour was <hi>touched with our infirmities,</hi> that he might be <hi>pitiful:</hi> I do think this Aſſembly thus called, is very much <hi>touched with the</hi> common <hi>infirmity</hi> of the Saints; and I hope that will teach you to pity others; that ſo Saints of one ſort may not be our intereſt; but that we may have reſpect unto all, though of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119106:22"/> different judgments; And if I did ſeem to ſpeak any thing that might ſeem to reflect upon thoſe of the <hi>Presbyterian Judgment,</hi> I think, if you have not an intereſt of love for them, will hardly anſwer this faithfulneſs to his Saints. I confeſs, in my pilgrimage, and ſome exerciſes I have had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, I did read that Scripture often in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 41 and 19. When God gave me and ſome of my fellows, what he would there and elſewhere, which he performed for us, and what would he do? to what end? <hi>That he might plant in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs the Cedar, and the Shitta tree, and the Mirtle tree, and the Palm tree together.</hi> To what end? <hi>That they might know, and conſider, and understand together, that the hand of the Lord hath done this;</hi> And that the Lord hath created it, that he wrought all ſalvation and deliverance, which he hath wrought, for the good of the whole flock; therefore I beſeech you (but I think I need not) have a care of the whole flock, love all the Sheep, love the Lambs, love all, and tender all, and cheriſh all, and countenance all, in all things that are good; and if the pooreſt Chriſtian, the moſt miſtaken Chriſtian, ſhould deſire to live peaceably and quietly under you, ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and humbly deſire to lead a life in godlineſs and honeſty; let him be protected.</p>
            <p>I think I need as little adviſe you concerning the <hi>propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel,</hi> and incouraging ſuch Miniſters and ſuch a Miniſtry, as be faithful in the Land, upon whom the true cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter is, Men that have truly received the ſpirit for ſuch a uſe, which Chriſtians will be well able to diſcern, and do; men that have received Gifts from him that aſcended on high, and led Captivity Captive, for the work before mentioned: and truly, the Apoſtle, <hi>Romans</hi> 12. when he had ſummoned up all the Mercies of God, and the goodneſs of God, (and hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of the foundations of the Goſpel, and of the ſeveral <hi>things</hi> that are the ſubject of his diſcourſe, in the 11 firſt <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>) after he hath beſonght them to offer up their Souls and Bodies a living ſacrifice to God, <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> he beſeecheth not to eſteem more highly of themſelves then they ought, but that they would be humble and ſober minded, and not ſtretch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves beyond their line; but they would have a care to thoſe that had received Gifts to theſe uſes there mentioned. I ſpeak not (it is far from my heart) for a <hi>Miniſtry deriving</hi> it ſelf
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119106:22"/> through <hi>the Papacy,</hi> and pretending to that which is ſo much inſiſted upon to be ſucceſſion: the true ſucceſſion is through <hi>the Spirit,</hi> given in that meaſure that the <hi>Spirit</hi> is given; and that is a right ſucceſſion; but I need not diſcourſe of theſe things to you; I am perſwaded you are taught of God, in a greater meaſure then my ſelf in theſe things; indeed I have but one word more to ſay, and that is, though in that perhaps I ſhall ſhew my weakneſs, it is by way of encouragement to you, to go on in this work.</p>
            <p>And give me leave to begin thus: I confeſs I never look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee ſuch a day as this, it may be nor you, <note place="margin" type="runSum">Owning Chriſt in accepting the Call.</note> when <hi>Jeſus Chriſt ſhall be owned</hi> as he is this day, and in <hi>this</hi> world <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is owned</hi> this day <hi>by you all,</hi> and you own him by your willingneſs in appearing here, and you manifeſt this (as far as poor <hi>creatures</hi> can) to be a day of <hi>the power of Chriſt</hi> by your willingneſs: <note place="margin">Pſa. 110.1.</note> I know you remember that Scripture in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 110.3. <hi>The people ſhall be willing in the day of thy Power;</hi> God doth manifeſt it to be a day of the power of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Having through ſo much blood, and ſo much trials as have been upon theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> made this to be one of the great iſſues thereof, <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Saints called to Rule.</note> to have a people called to <hi>the Supreme Authority</hi> upon ſuch <hi>an avowed account,</hi> God hath owned <hi>his Son by this,</hi> and you by your willingneſs do own <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for my part, I confeſs I did never look to ſee ſuch a ſight: perhaps you are not known by face one to another; but we muſt tell you this, that indeed we have not allowed our ſelves in the choyce of one perſon, in whom we had not this good hope, that there <hi>was Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and love unto all his Saints and People:</hi> And thus God hath owned you in the face and eyes of the world, and thus by your coming hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have you owned him, as it is in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 43.21. It is an high expreſſion, and look to your own hearts, whether now or hereafter God ſhall apply it to you: <note place="margin">Eſa. 43.21</note> 
               <hi>This people</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I have formed for my ſelf, that they might ſhew forth my praiſe.</hi> It is a memorable place, and I hope not unfitly applyed, God apply it to each of your hearts. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Why theſe called of God. 7. Reaſons:</note> I ſhall not deſcant upon the words, they are plain, you are as like the forming of <hi>God as ever people were:</hi> 
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. Their not ſeeking to come into Power.</note> if any man ſhould ask you one by one, and ſhould tender a Book to you, you would date to ſwear, that neither directly nor indirectly did you ſeek to come hither;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119106:23"/> you have been paſſive in coming hither, in being called hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that is an active word, <hi>This people I have formed.</hi> Conſider the Circumſtances, by which you are called toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, through what diſſiculties, through what ſtrivings, through what blood you are come hither; Neither you nor I, nor no man living, three moneths ago, had a thought to have ſeen ſuch a company, taking upon them, or rather being called to the ſupreme Authority; and therefore own your call.</p>
            <p>Indeed, I think, as it may be truly ſaid, that never was a ſupreme Authority, conſiſting of ſo numerous a Body as you are, which I believe are above 140, were never in the ſupreme Authority, under ſuch a Notion, in ſuch a way of owning of God, and being owned by him; and therefore I ſay alſo, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a people formed for ſuch a purpoſe (ſo called) if it were time to compare your ſtanding with thoſe that have been called by the ſuffrages of the people, who can tell how ſoon God may fit the People for ſuch a thing, and who would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire any thing more in the world, but that it might be ſo? I would all the Lords people were Prophets, I would they were fit to be called, and fit to call; <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Reaſon why the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not fit to chuſe, becauſe not owning Chriſts inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</note> and it is the longing of our hearts to ſee them once own the INTEREST OF JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST; and give me leave to ſay, if I know any thing in the world, what is there more like to win the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the Intereſt and love of God? Nay, what a duty will lye upon you to have your converſation ſuch, as that they may love you, that they may ſee you lay out your time and ſpirits for them? Is not this the moſt likely way to bring them to their <hi>Liberties?</hi> and do you not by this put it upon God to finde the time and the ſeaſon for it? by powring forth his <hi>Spirit,</hi> at leaſt by convincing them, <note place="margin" type="runSum">Regal pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, thraldom &amp; bondage.</note> that as men fearing God have fought them out of their thraldome and bondage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Regal Power, ſo men fearing God rule them in the fear of God, and take care to adminiſter good unto them; but this is ſome digreſſion. (I ſay) own your call; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is marvellous, and it is of God, <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Reaſon, unthought of, unproje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by them</note> and it hath been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>projected, <hi>unthought of by you and us;</hi> and that hath been the way God hath dealt with us all along, to keep <hi>things</hi> from our eyes; <hi>that what</hi> we have acted, we have ſeen nothing before us; which alſo is a witneſs in ſome meaſure to our <hi>integrity;</hi> (I ſay) you are called with a high Call, and why ſhould we
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119106:23"/> be afraid to ſay, or think, <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Becauſe agreeable to the Word of Promiſe</note> that this way, may be the door to uſher in things that God hath promiſed and propheſied of, and to ſet the hearts of his people to wait for, and expect? We know <hi>who</hi> they are that ſhall <hi>war WITH THE LAMB</hi> againſt his enemies. <note place="margin">Rev. 17.14 19.14.</note> They ſhall <hi>BE</hi> a people <hi>CALLED, CHOSEN AND FAITHFUL,</hi> and hath in the <hi>Military</hi> way, (we muſt ſpeak it without <hi>flattery</hi>) I believe you know it, he hath acted with them, and for them, and now in the Civil <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> and theſe are not ill Prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations for that good we wait for: <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. Becauſe called upon the account of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the way that God did all thy work in the Army.</note> indeed, I do think ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is at the door, we are at the threſhold, and therefore it becomes us to lift up our heads, and to encourage our ſelves in the Lord: and we have ſome of us <hi>thought</hi> it our duty to endeavour this way, not vainly looking on that Propheſie in <hi>Daniel,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2.44.</note> 
               <hi>And the Kingdom ſhall not be delivered to another peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Truly, God hath brought it into your hands, by his owning and bleſſing, and calling out a <hi>Military</hi> Power, God hath perſwaded their hearts to be inſtrumental in calling you, and this hath been ſet upon our hearts, and upon all the faithful in the Land, <note place="margin" type="runSum">5. Called by the Saints.</note> it may be that it is not our duty to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it over to any other people, and <hi>that Scripture</hi> may be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling now to us, but I may be beyond my line.</p>
            <p>But I <hi>thank</hi> God, I have my hopes exerciſed in theſe things, and ſo I am perſwaded are yours: truly, ſeeing that theſe things are ſo, that you are at the edge of the Promiſes and Propheſies, at leaſt if there were neither Promiſe for this nor Propheſie, your coveting the beſt things, endeavouring after the beſt things, and as I have ſaid elſewhere, if I were to chuſe the meaneſt Officer in the Army or Commonwealth, <note place="margin" type="runSum">The moſt Prudential way.</note> I would chuſe a <hi>godly Man that hath Principles, eſpecially where truſt is to be committed,</hi> becauſe I know where to have a man that hath Principles. I believe if any man of you ſhould chuſe a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, you <hi>would do ſo,</hi> and I would all our Magiſtrates were <hi>ſo choſen, that may be ſome effect of this;</hi> it is our duty to chuſe <hi>men that fear the Lord, to praiſe the Lord,</hi> yea, <note place="margin" type="runSum">6. Becauſe ſuch ſhould praiſe the Lord in their work.</note> ſuch as the Lord forms for himſelf, and he expects not praiſes from others: this being ſo, it puts me in mind of another Scripture, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 68.22. which indeed is a glorious Propheſie, and I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded fo the Goſpel, or it may be of the Jews; alſo there
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119106:24"/> it is propheſied, <hi>He will bring his people again out of the depths of the Sea, as once he led Iſrael through the red Sea;</hi> and it may be ſome do think God is bringing the Jews home to their ſtation from the Iſles of the Sea: ſurely when God ſets up the glory of the Goſpel-Church, it ſhall be gathering people out of deep waters, out of the multitude of waters; ſuch are his people, drawn out of the multitudes of the Nations, and people of the world. And that <hi>Pſalm</hi> will be very glorious in many other parts of it, <hi>When he gave the word, great was the company of them that publiſhed it; Kings of the Armies did flee apace, and ſhe that tarried at home divided the ſpoyl: and although ye have lain among the Pots, yet ſhall ye be as the wings of a Dove covered with ſiver, and her feathers with yellow gold.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the triumph of that <hi>Pſalm</hi> is exceeding high and great, and God is accompliſhing it; and the cloſe of it, that clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with my heart, and I am perſwaded will with yours al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; That <hi>God ſhakes Hills and Mountains, and they reel,</hi> and God hath a Hill too, <hi>and his Hill is as the Hill of Baſhan, and the Chariots of God are twenty thouſand of Angels, and God will dwell upon this Hill for ever.</hi> Truly, I am ſorry that I have troubled you, in ſuch a place of heat as this is, ſo long; all that I have to ſay in mine own Name, and in the Names of my Fellow-Officers, (who have joyned with me in this work) That we ſhall commend you to the Grace of GOD, and to the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his Spirit, having thus far ſerved you, (or rather OUR LORD JESUS CHRIST IN IT) we are, as we hope, and ſhall be, ready in our ſtations, according as the Providence of God ſhall lead us, <note place="margin" type="runSum">Promiſing Subjection.</note> to be ſubſervient to the Work of God, and the Authority (which <hi>we reckon</hi>) <hi>God hath ſet over us.</hi> 
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">7. Becauſe the Officers both by Sea and Land, the Churches and godly people of the Nation, (unſought for, unprojected) gave their hearty concurrence and deſire, herein.</note> And Although we have no Formal thing to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with, to which the hands and outward viſible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the hearts of the Officers of the three Nations are ſet, yet we may ſay for them, and we may ſay alſo with confidence for our Brethren at Sea, with whom neither in <hi>Scotland</hi> nor <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor at Sea, hath any Artifice been uſed
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119106:24"/> to perſwade their Approbations to this work: yet we can ſay, That their conſent and affections hath flowed in to us from all parts beyond our expectations; and we are confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent we may ſay with all confidence, That we have had their approbations, and full conſent, unſought indeed to the other work, ſo that you have their hearts and affections in this; and not onely they, but we have very many Papers from the Churches of God, throughout the Nation wonderfully both approving what hath been done in removing Obſtacles, and approving what we have done in this very thing. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaid this, I ſhall trouble you no more; but if you will be pleaſed <hi>that this inſtrument</hi> may be read, which I have ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the advice of the Council of Officers, we ſhall then laave you to your own thoughts, and to the guidance of God, to order and diſpoſe of your ſelves for further Meetings as you ſhall ſee cauſe.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Acts 11.51.</bibl>
                  <p>And this ſpake he, not of himſelf; but being high Prieſt that year, he propheſied.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="application">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:119106:25"/>
            <head>A Brief Application ON The Foregoing PAPERS.</head>
            <p>ARe theſe things ſo? Have we been, and are we ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly engaged to the advancement <hi>of Chriſts Kingdom,</hi> by carrying on a thorow Reformation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word of God?</p>
            <p>Has there been <hi>a Cauſe of Gods and Chriſts</hi> pleaded and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, which the upright-hearted in theſe Nations have own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and adhered to, and which the ſuperſtitious, wicked and prophane have ſcorned and oppoſed?</p>
            <p>Have we been pleading and engaging to blood <hi>for Chriſt</hi> againſt <hi>Antichriſt?</hi> And is it ſo, that the <hi>Military work</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver throve until it was put upon <hi>that avowed accompt,</hi> (viz.) <hi>men of Principles, fearing God,</hi> engaged in it, and making that the avowed qualification to admit into Office and Truſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt them?</p>
            <p>Hath <hi>Charles the Father, and his Biſhops?</hi> Charles <hi>the Son, and his Scotiſh Presbytery,</hi> as Tyrannous and Antichriſtian, beaſtly and whoriſh, <hi>as the heads of the falſe Magiſtracy and Miniſtry,</hi> as Enemies to the Kingdom and Intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt, and Supporters of the Throne of the Beaſt; been, with all their Adherents by Sea and Land, engaged with, vanquiſht and ſubdued, broken like Potters veſſels, and the righteous judgments of God executed upon many of the heads of them as Traytors and Rebels?</p>
            <p>Was <hi>King and Kingſhip,</hi> as ſtanding in oppoſition to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> being as was ſaid, one of the ten horns of the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. taken away?</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119106:25"/>
            <p>Was the <hi>Parliamentary Authority</hi> defaced, garbled, purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and at laſt utterly broke, as Obſtructers hereof, <hi>and that by the Army</hi> at their deſire, and to the great joy of moſt of the godly in the Land, as having loſt the <hi>Spirit of the Cauſe,</hi> and ſo far degenerated into a <hi>ſelfiſh and perſecuting Spirit,</hi> that there appeared an enmity thereto?</p>
            <p>And laſtly, was there <hi>another people</hi> called eminently by the Lord, to own, aſſert and carry on this cauſe and intereſt of Chriſts Kingly Authority, to whom all <hi>due ſubjection</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed for <hi>Christs ſake, as to an Authority God had ſet over them</hi> to ſuch an end?</p>
            <p>
               <label>1 <hi>Queſt.</hi>
               </label> Whether it will not neceſſarily follow, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Parliament, Army, Miniſters, and others,</hi> that have thus ſtated, aſſerted, engaged in ſuch a cauſe <hi>as Gods and Chriſts,</hi> and founding it upon the Word of God, to the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and breaking all viſible Rule and Government, which for ſo many hundred years hath in Church and State been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us in theſe Nations, have either been groſly deluded, and ſo become guilty of all the blood that hath been ſpilt in this quarrel, and conſequently a company of Munſter-ſpirited Tyrants, Traytors and Murderers, as it hath been reflected upon them, and ſo ought to repent in duſt and aſhes, and to endeavour all due ſatisfaction poſſible to Cavaleers, Scots, Prelates and Presbyters; or if ſtated upon ſound principles of Truth and Righteouſneſs, which the Lord hath eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly owned and led to, ſtep by ſtep, and that all this ſhaking, overturning, that hath been made in <hi>Church and State,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the pulling down of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and exalting <hi>the Kingdom of his Son,</hi> is warranted and juſtified by the holy Scripture; <hi>then doubtleſs</hi> ought this Cauſe to be owned, adhered unto, and preſt after, with all zeal and fidelity, and they are to be eſteemed Apoſtates, Revolters and Backſliders, that ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline or turn aſide herefrom?</p>
            <p>
               <label>2 <hi>Queſt.</hi>
               </label> Whether the <hi>Army,</hi> who in ſo much ſeeming light and love to God, bringing <hi>this glorious cauſe into the hands of his people,</hi> (having broken down the National conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) <hi>with a declared ſubjection to them for Chriſts ſake,</hi> are not guilty of moſt dreadful Apoſtacy and Rebellion againſt him, his Crown and Dignity?</p>
            <p>Firſt, in breaking that <hi>Aſſembly</hi> ſo by the <hi>Lord</hi> in that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119106:26"/> manner called together, whilſt in the faithful proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the ſaid cauſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in ſetting up their <hi>Apoſtate General,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>his Son,</hi> even in contradiction to all the <hi>Lords</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſul works amongſt us, as <hi>heads of Church and State,</hi> and to whom were made all thoſe <hi>blaſphemous dreadſul Addreſſes,</hi> Oaths and Engagements, to the licking up their vomit again, owning and eſtabliſhing all the <hi>Pride, Tyranny and Idolatry</hi> under new names and pretences, that had been ſo contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly caſt down amongſt us, <hi>(viz.) Kingſhip, Peerage</hi> and <hi>Prelacy,</hi> under the terms of <hi>Protector,</hi> an <hi>Other Houſe</hi> and <hi>Tryers,</hi> who being ſet up, and <hi>an aſſay made</hi> to confirm all by <hi>Parliament,</hi> their Counſel being confounded, ſo that they could not bring about their Enterpriſes, <hi>as</hi> a further fruit of backſliding, <hi>the Army have ſought out another invention</hi> to withſtand the true heir the Lord Jeſus, and kept him from his right, by calling together ſuch as formerly were by them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, <hi>for want of ſpirit, and being in oppoſition to the Lords work;</hi> and that it was ſo in truth, have not <hi>very many of them</hi> given ſufficient evidence, by being <hi>Principals in the late Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy?</hi> and <hi>the generality ſuch</hi> as ſtuck not to lift up their hands to the moſt High, that they would be true and faithful to the now <hi>depoſed Uſurper?</hi> And thoſe few of renown amongſt them, whoſe integrity was tryed, it 's to be feared, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, may ſerve for little more then to give countenance to what further their deceived hearts are luſting after, of which ſome proof is already given in their votes for continuing the oppreſſion in paying Tythes, keeping from ſale <hi>Hampton Court</hi> and <hi>White hall;</hi> but more eſpecially their Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity ſufficiently juſtifying the wicked, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemning the righteous.</p>
            <p>
               <label>3 <hi>Queſt.</hi>
               </label> Whether they who have owned the Lord in all his diſpenſations in the midſt of all theſe oppoſitions and declenſion of others, ought not to be eſteemed the well-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the Cauſe of God, his people and this Nation? ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſlanderouſly reported Munſter-ſpirited and fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Obj.</label> What would theſe people have? The Cavaleeres old and new, with the Commonwealths-men, have ſomewhat to offer; but theſe neither know what they ſay, or whereof they affirm.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119106:26"/>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Were it granted they were ſo weak as not to be able to hold forth ſome well-compoſed Model of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being ſtill it may be better at pulling down, as is ſaid page 24. line 10. then building up and eſtabliſhing works; is this a good Argument to ſlight any rational diſſatisfaction to what is now ſet up? If <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> had never been taken away until ſome well ordered Church Government had been offered to ſucceed it by <hi>the Puritans,</hi> (who were then eſteemed as ignoraut, giddy and fanatique becauſe they did not) would it not have remained to this day? But for further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there are four things <hi>in the Aſſirmative,</hi> wherein there ſeems to be a general agreement amongſt this people, tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much to ſettlement upon a righteous Foundation.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>1. In reference to their Soveraign,</head>
               <p>That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt (in whoſe Name, and by whoſe bleſſing and ſtrength the mighty works have been effected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, <hi>againſt Tyranny in the Civil, and Antichriſtianiſm in the Eccleſiaſtick State</hi>) may be publickly owned <hi>Our only Lord and King;</hi> from whom, as the head, all Power, Rule and Authority in Church and State, is to be derived, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to every other Title; without which alteration, ſince the Foundations are out of courſe, it will be utterly impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible there ſhould be any ſubſiſtence for that: <hi>the Image-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or fourth Beaſts conſtitution,</hi> muſt as certainly be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturned and broken, to give way to this <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> as the other were broken to give way to the fourth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>1 Tim. 6.15. <hi>He is the bleſſed and onely Potentate, King of kings, and Lord of lords.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>John 5.27. <hi>And hath given him Authority to execute judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo: becauſe he is the Son of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſaiah 9.6. <hi>The Government ſhall be upon his ſhoulders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obj.</label> How can Chriſt be ſaid to be <hi>our King?</hi> is he not in heaven?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> 
                  <hi>God</hi> was <hi>Iſraels King</hi> of old, though heaven was his habitation, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> ſate on the <hi>Throne of the Lord,</hi> 1 Chron. 29.23. 2 Chron. 9.8.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Iſrael</hi> would imitate other Nations in making them
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119106:27"/> a <hi>King,</hi> they did not reject <hi>Samuel,</hi> but the <hi>Lord</hi> from raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over them, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Gideen</hi> ſaid unto them, <hi>I will not rule over you, neither ſhall my Son; the Lord ſhall rule over them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why therefore ſhould it be thought ſtrange, that <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> ſhould be admitted to his regal Authority, though in Heaven, to whom the <hi>Father</hi> hath given all power in Heaven and Earth? And why may not <hi>Chriſt</hi> be owned <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>State</hi> as of the <hi>Church,</hi> there being hundreds of Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons through grace in theſe Nations, that admit of no other <hi>Head or Law-giver</hi> in the Church? And why may he not as well Rule over and amongſt us, as ſuffer with us all the time of <hi>Antichriſts Reign,</hi> all that is done to <hi>his,</hi> being done unto <hi>himſelf?</hi> And theſe things are aſſerted in the Covenant, but more fully by the General and Officers of the Army in their fore-mentioned Letters and Declarations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>2. In reference to Laws,</head>
               <p>That the <hi>Laws</hi> of this great <hi>King,</hi> as they are recorded in <hi>the Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> remaining in force ſince <hi>his death,</hi> be the declared Laws of this Nation, in oppoſition to the Heatheniſh, Tyrannous and Popiſh Laws yet in force amongſt us.</p>
               <p>Iſai. 8.19. <hi>Should not a people ſeek unto their god? to the Laws, to the Teſtimonies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſa. 23.22. <hi>The Lord is our Law-giver, he is our King, he will ſave us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jam. 4.12. <hi>There is one Law-giver, who is able to ſave and to deſtroy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Deut. 4.8. <hi>What Nation ſo great as hath ſtatutes and judgments ſo righteous as all this Law ſet before you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Keep therefore and do them: for this is your wiſdome and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding in the ſight of the Nations, which ſhall hear all theſe ſtatutes, and ſay, Surely this generation is a wiſe and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Deut. 17.18,19,20. <hi>And it ſhall be when he ſitteth upon the Throne of his Kingdom, that he ſhall write him a copy of this Law in a book: and it ſhall be with him, and he ſhall read therein all the days of his life, that he may learn to fear the Lord his God, that his heart be not lifted up above his brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119106:27"/>
               <p>It's a Maxime in the Law, aſſerted by <hi>Finch</hi> the great Lawyer, <hi>Cook</hi> and others, that no Act of Parliament, or Law repugnant to the Law of God, is of any force: but how well our Law-makers have lived up hereto, read Mr. <hi>Boon's Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men legum Angliae;</hi> who comparing our Laws with the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, finds 68 Laws expreſly contrary to the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Read that excellent Letter of <hi>Eleutherius</hi> to King <hi>Lucius,</hi> page 8. what light herein was declared for in that day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>3. In reference to the Adminiſtrators.</head>
               <p>That the people <hi>moſt read,</hi> and beſt <hi>practicers of this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and perfect Law,</hi> be choſen out to the Adminiſtration thereof under Chriſt, in oppoſition to the ignorant, prophane and ſcandalous; and all, <hi>both old and new Malignants,</hi> that have viſibly oppoſed him in his Word and Works, and not given ſome ſuitable teſtimony of repentance.</p>
               <p>Exod. 18.21. Num. 11.16. Deut. 1.13. <hi>Thouſhalt provide of all the people, able men, ſuch as fear God, men of truth, hating co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs; and place ſuch over them to be Rulers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2 Sam. 23.2,3,4. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord ſpake, and the Rock of Iſrael ſaid, He that rules over men, muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſai. 1.26. <hi>And I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Counſellors as at the beginning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which principle is further aſſerted,</p>
               <p n="1">1. By the <hi>Armies Petition,</hi> 13 <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1652. who pray, <q rend="inline">that only men fearing God, and hating covetouſneſs, ſhould be put into places of Authority and Truſt, and that all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, ſcandalous and diſaffected perſons ſhould be outed; and the neglect hereof, given as one of the grounds of the Parliaments diſſolution.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By the preſent Aſſembly at <hi>Westminſter</hi> in their Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <hi>May</hi> 9. 1659. <q rend="inline">That all ſuch as ſhall be in any place of Truſt and Power within this Commonwealth, <hi>be able for the diſcharge of ſuch Truſt, and that they be perſons fearing God, that have given teſtimony of their true love to all the people of God, and of their faithfuineſs to the cauſe of this Commonwealth,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Declaration of the ſeventh of May, 1659. in which Declaration they further ſay, That they ſhall vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119106:28"/> endeavour the carrying on of Reformation ſo much deſired, and ſo often declared for, to <hi>the end there may be a godly and faithful Magiſtracy and Ministry upheld in theſe Nations, to the glory and praiſe of our Lord Jeſus Christ, and to the</hi> reviving and making glad the hearts of the upright in the Land.</q> But how well theſe good words are put in practice, look within their own walls, and may you not finde divers of the late <hi>Tyrants</hi> Council, that perſecuted and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned ſo many of Gods people for their faithful witneſs to the Cauſe?</p>
               <p>Is not their Speaker one of the new upſtart Lords? and are there not many others of the ſame ſtamp that ſate in the Other Houſe?</p>
               <p>How many are there that ſwore Allegiance and fidelity, both to the deceaſed and late depoſed Protector?</p>
               <p>How many ſcandalous perſons?</p>
               <p>How many unworthy Mercenary Lawyers?</p>
               <p>And will theſe men paſs for men fearing God, true Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Gods people, and faithful to the Cauſe? <hi>Are ſuch like to carry on a vigorous and thorow Reformation ſo much deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to the glory and praiſe of our Lord Jeſus Christ, and making glad the hearts of the upright?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>4. In reference to the Eccleſiaſtical State.</head>
               <p n="1">1. That a thorow Reformation be preſt after, according as is expreſt in the Covenant, agreeable to the Word of God, and beſt reformed Churches.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That ſuch a Miniſtry may without reſtraint go forth, as are faithful, and have received the Spirit, and gifts from on high for ſuch a work, and that are made able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, accepting Chriſts work out of love to ſouls, together with ſuch wages as he hath left in his word.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That all Eccleſiaſtical Officers and Offices (ſo called) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon the Hierarchy, may be extirpated root and branch, whether Parſons, Vicars, Curates, Patrons, &amp;c. with their Maintenance, Tythes, Offerings, Oblations, Obventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Tenths, Firſt-Fruits, as deriving their Riſe and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> ſupported by the <hi>Beast,</hi> and for which there is not the leaſt footing in the Word of God.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119106:28"/>
               <p n="4">4. That the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> intermeddle not in the matters of <hi>Chriſts Church, or Spiritual concernment,</hi> impoſing either <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry maintenance, or forms of worſhip,</hi> ſuited to his intereſt; which hath been the ground of all body and ſoul-oppreſſion.</p>
               <p>Theſe being faithfully obſerved, will adminiſter equal and impartial juſtice to every one, and tend to the recovery of the <hi>primitive</hi> (and propheſied to be reſtored) <hi>Ordinance of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, making it a terrour to evil doers, and a praiſe to them that do well,</hi> ſo that none in well-doing, of what perſwaſion ſoever, can have cauſe to doubt of being protected in their perſons and proprieties from ſuch as ſhall attempt upon any pretence whatſoever to invade <hi>the</hi> ſame, or of being in an equal <hi>capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> with others qualified for electing or being elected to a <hi>participation</hi> of Rule, as any <hi>ability</hi> for the ſame may be given to <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <list>
               <item>Page 23. line 35. for <hi>politick,</hi> read <hi>publick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 25. line 16. for <hi>thereby,</hi> read <hi>then by.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 33. line 8. for <hi>petitioned for,</hi> read <hi>pretended to.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>There are other leſſer faults; but theſe needfully require amendment with the Pen, or mention of them in an <hi>Errata.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
